<resources>
    <string name="app_name">ThessApp</string>
    <string name="title_activity_main">Main</string>

    <string-array name="array_markeritems_texts">
        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Arch of Galerius</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Gr.</a>: αψίδα του Γαλερίου) (or <b>Kamara</b>, <a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Gr.</a>:καμάρα) and the <b>Rotunda</b> (ροτόντα) are neighboring early 4th-century monuments in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, in the region of <a href="/wiki/Central_Macedonia" title="Central Macedonia">Central Macedonia</a> in northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. The Rotunda is also known as the <b>Church of Agios Georgios</b> or (in English) the <b><a href="/wiki/Rotunda_(architecture)" title="Rotunda (architecture)">Rotunda</a> of <a href="/wiki/St._George" title="St. George" class="mw-redirect">St. George</a></b>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The 4th-century <a href="/wiki/Roman_Emperor" title="Roman Emperor" class="mw-redirect">Roman Emperor</a> <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> commissioned these two structures as elements of an imperial precinct linked to his Thessaloniki palace. <a href="/wiki/Archeologists" title="Archeologists" class="mw-redirect">Archeologists</a> have found substantial remains of the palace to the southwest.<sup id="cite_ref-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> These three monumental structures were connected by a road that ran through the arch, which rose above the major east-west road of the city.</p>
            <p>At the crux of the major axes of the city, the Arch of Galerius emphasized the power of the emperor and linked the monumental structures with the fabric of 4th-century Thessaloniki. The arch was composed of a masonry core faced with <a href="/wiki/Marble" title="Marble">marble</a> sculptural panels celebrating a victory over the <a href="/wiki/Sassanid_Empire" title="Sassanid Empire" class="mw-redirect">Sassanid Persians</a>. About two-thirds the arch is preserved.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda was a massive circular structure with a masonry core that had an <a href="/wiki/Oculus" title="Oculus">oculus</a> like the <a href="/wiki/Pantheon,_Rome" title="Pantheon, Rome">Pantheon</a> in Rome. It has gone through multiple periods of use and modification as a polytheist temple, a Christian basilica, a Muslim mosque, and again a Christian church (and archaeological site). A minaret is preserved from its use as a mosque, and ancient remains are exposed on its southern side.</p>

            <h2>Location and description of the Arch</h2>
            <p>Arch of Galerius, stands on what is now <i>Egnatia &amp; Dimitrios Gounari Street</i>. The arch was built in 298 to 299 AD and dedicated in 303 AD to celebrate the victory of the <a href="/wiki/Tetrarchy" title="Tetrarchy">tetrarch</a> <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> over the <a href="/wiki/Sassanid_Empire" title="Sassanid Empire" class="mw-redirect">Sassanid Persians</a> and capture of their capital <a href="/wiki/Ctesiphon" title="Ctesiphon">Ctesiphon</a> in 298.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> The structure was an octopylon (eight-pillared gateway) forming a triple arch that was built of a rubble masonry core faced first with brick and then with marble panels with sculptural relief. The central arched opening was 9.7 m wide and 12.5 m high, and the secondary openings on other side were 4.8 m wide and 6.5 m high. The central arch spanned the portion of the <i><a href="/wiki/Via_Egnatia" title="Via Egnatia">Via Egnatia</a></i> (primary Roman road from Dyrrhacium to <a href="/wiki/Byzantium" title="Byzantium">Byzantium</a>) that passed through the city as a <a href="/wiki/Decumanus_Maximus" title="Decumanus Maximus"><i>Decumanus</i></a> (east-west major street). A road connecting the Rotunda (125m northeast) with the Palace complex (235m southwest) passed through the arch along its long axis.</p>
            <p>Only the northwestern three of the eight pillars and parts of the <a href="/wiki/Masonry" title="Masonry">masonry</a> cores of the arches above survive: i.e., the entire eastern side (4 pillars) and the southernmost one of the western pillars are lost.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Extensive consolidation with modern brick has been performed on the exposed masonry cores to protect the monument. The two pillars flanking the central arched passageway retain their sculpted <a href="/wiki/Marble" title="Marble">marble</a> slabs, which depict the wars of Galerius against the Persians in broadly panegyric terms.</p>

            <h3>Sculptural program of the Arch</h3>
            <p>Understanding of the sculptural program of the arch is limited by the loss of the majority of the marble panels, but the remains give an impression of the whole. Four vertically stacked registers of sculpted decoration were carved on each pillar, each separated by elaborate moldings. A label for the <a href="/wiki/Tigris_River" title="Tigris River" class="mw-redirect">Tigris River</a> indicates that there were likely labels on other representations as the builders deemed necessary. Artistic license was taken in the representations, for instance, the Caesar Galerius is shown in personal combat with the Sassanid Shah Narses in one of the panels; although they never met in battle.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> On the arch a mounted Galerius attacks a similarly mounted Narses with a lance as an eagle bearing a victory wreath in its talons approaches Galerius. The Caesar sits securely on his rearing horse, while the Persian king appears nearly unhorsed. Terrified Persians cower under the hooves of the Caesar’s horse in the chaos of battle. The panel expresses the power of the Caesar Galerius.</p>
            <p>The relief of the imperial family conjoined in a sacrifice of thanksgiving owes its distant prototype to the Augustan reliefs on the <i><a href="/wiki/Ara_Pacis" title="Ara Pacis">Ara Pacis</a></i> in Rome.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> Galerius\' wife, Diocletian\'s daughter Valeria, is shown at his side, helping authenticate his connection to his predecessor. Here as elsewhere all the faces have been carefully chiselled off, whether as <i><a href="/wiki/Damnatio_memoriae" title="Damnatio memoriae">damnatio memoriae</a></i> or in later cultural intolerance of images.</p>
                <p>In another panel, the tetrarchs are all arrayed in the toga as a <i>Victoria</i> holds a victory wreath out to the heads of the two <i>Augusti</i>. A third panel celebrates the unity of the <a href="/wiki/Tetrarchy" title="Tetrarchy">tetrarchy</a>, with a depiction of the tetrarchs standing together; the depersonalized manner in which the tetrarchs are portrayed is reminiscent of the schematic statues of the tetrarchs in porphyry at <a href="/wiki/St._Mark%%27s_Basilica" title="St. Mark\'s Basilica" class="mw-redirect">St. Mark\'s Basilica</a> in Venice.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> Only Galerius is dressed in armor, and he makes the offering upon the altar.</p>
            <p>What remains of the arch asserts the glory of the tetrarchy and the prominence of Galerius within that system. The arch celebrates the Roman Empire as part of Galerius’ victory over the Sassanid king.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> On the right pictured, is Galerius on his horse in an attack on a Sassanid guard.</p>

            <h2>Rotunda of Galerius</h2>
            <p>The Rotunda of Galerius is 125m northeast of the Arch of Galerius at 40°37\'59.77"N, 22°57\'9.77"E. It is also known (by its consecration and use) as the <a href="/wiki/Church_of_Greece" title="Church of Greece">Greek Orthodox</a> Church of <i><a href="/wiki/Saint_George" title="Saint George">Agios Georgios</a></i>, and is informally called the Church of the Rotunda (or simply <i>The Rotunda</i>). The cylindrical structure was built in 306 AD on the orders of the tetrarch <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a>, who was thought to have intended it to be his <a href="/wiki/Mausoleum" title="Mausoleum">mausoleum</a>. It was more likely intended as a temple; it is not known to what god it would have been dedicated.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda has a diameter of 24.5 m. Its walls are more than 6 m thick, which is why it has withstood Thessaloniki\'s earthquakes. The walls are interrupted by eight rectangular bays, with the south bay forming the entrance. A flat brick dome, 30 m high at the peak, crowns the cylindrical structure. In its original design, the dome of the Rotunda had an <i><a href="/wiki/Oculus" title="Oculus">oculus</a></i>, as does the <a href="/wiki/Pantheon,_Rome" title="Pantheon, Rome">Pantheon</a> in Rome.</p>

            <h3>Uses of the Rotunda</h3>
            <p>After Galerius\'s death in 311, he was buried at <a href="/wiki/Gamzigrad" title="Gamzigrad">Gamzigrad</a> (<a href="/wiki/Felix_Romuliana" title="Felix Romuliana" class="mw-redirect">Felix Romuliana</a>) near <a href="/wiki/Zajecar" title="Zajecar" class="mw-redirect">Zajecar</a>, <a href="/wiki/Serbia" title="Serbia">Serbia</a>. The Rotunda stood empty for several years until the Emperor <a href="/wiki/Constantine_I" title="Constantine I" class="mw-redirect">Constantine I</a> ordered it converted into a Christian church in 326. The church was embellished with very high quality <a href="/wiki/Mosaics" title="Mosaics" class="mw-redirect">mosaics</a>. Only fragments have survived of the original decoration, for example, a band depicting saints with hands raised in prayer, in front of complex architectural fantasies.</p>
            <p>The building was used as a church for over 1,200 years until the city fell to the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottomans</a>. In 1590 it was converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a>, called the Mosque of Suleyman Hortaji Effendi, and a <a href="/wiki/Minaret" title="Minaret">minaret</a> was added to the structure. It was used as a mosque until 1912, when the Greeks captured the city during the <a href="/wiki/Balkan_War" title="Balkan War" class="mw-redirect">Balkan War</a>. Greek Orthodox officials reconsecrated the structure as a church, and they left the minaret. The structure was damaged during an earthquake in 1978 but was subsequently restored. As of 2004<sup class="plainlinks noprint asof-tag update" style="display:none;"><a class="external text" href="//en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arch_of_Galerius_and_Rotunda&amp;action=edit">[update]</a></sup>, the minaret was still being stabilized with scaffolding. The building is now a historical monument under the <a href="/w/index.php?title=Ephorate_of_Byzantine_Antiquities&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities (page does not exist)">Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities</a> of the <a href="/wiki/Greek_Ministry_of_Culture" title="Greek Ministry of Culture" class="mw-redirect">Greek Ministry of Culture</a>, although the Greek Orthodox Church has access to the church for various festivities.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda is the oldest of Thessaloniki\'s churches. Some Greek publications claim it is the oldest Christian church in the world, although there are competitors for that title. It is the most important surviving example of a church from the early Christian period of the Greek-speaking part of the Roman Empire.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Navarinou Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Πλατεία Ναβαρίνου</span>) is a <a href="/wiki/Town_square" title="Town square">square</a> in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The square dates back to the Roman period of the city, with the ruins of the palace of <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> located within it. The square is also the site of <a href="/wiki/Massacre_of_Thessalonica" title="Massacre of Thessalonica">Massacre of Thessalonica</a> which took place during the reign of <a href="/wiki/Theodosius_I" title="Theodosius I">Theodosius I</a>.</p>
            <p>Today it is a popular meeting place, mainly amongst the student population of the city.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <a href="/wiki/Roman_Forum" title="Roman Forum">Roman Forum</a> of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> is the ancient Roman-era <a href="/wiki/Forum_(Roman)" title="Forum (Roman)">forum</a> (or <i>Agora</i>) of the city, located at the upper side of <a href="/wiki/Aristotelous_Square" title="Aristotelous Square">Aristotelous Square</a>.</p>
            <p>It is a large two-terraced forum<sup id="cite_ref-Frommer.27s_Greece_Forum_1_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Frommer.27s_Greece_Forum_1-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> featuring two-storey <a href="/wiki/Stoa" title="Stoa">stoas</a>, dug up by accident in the 1960s. The forum complex also boasts two <a href="/wiki/Roman_baths" title="Roman baths" class="mw-redirect">Roman baths</a>,<sup id="cite_ref-A_Companion_1_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-A_Companion_1-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> one of which has been excavated while the other is buried underneath the city, and a small theater which was also used for <a href="/wiki/Gladiatorial_games" title="Gladiatorial games" class="mw-redirect">gladiatorial games</a>. Although the initial complex was not built in Roman times, it was largely refurbished in the 2nd century.<sup id="cite_ref-A_Companion_1_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-A_Companion_1-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> It is believed that the forum and the theater continued to be used until at least the 6th century.<sup id="cite_ref-From_Early_Roman_3-0" class="reference">
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Agias Sofias Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Πλατεία Αγίας Σοφίας</span>) is a <a href="/wiki/Town_square" title="Town square">square</a> in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The square dates back to the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Greece" title="Byzantine Greece">Byzantine</a> period of the city and took its name from the church of <a href="/wiki/Hagia_Sophia,_Thessaloniki" title="Hagia Sophia, Thessaloniki">Hagia Sophia</a> (<i>Holy Wisdom</i>) located within it. At the time is was also called <i>Skalia</i>. During a fire in 1890, it was heavily damaged but was restored under the supervision of <a href="/wiki/Charles_Diehl" title="Charles Diehl">Charles Diehl</a>, a notable Byzantinist.</p>
            <p>Although not a square today, plans have been released which include the complete redevelopment of the area with a new square and pedestrianized zone to extent from the <a href="/wiki/Church_of_the_Acheiropoietos" title="Church of the Acheiropoietos">Church of the Acheiropoietos</a> to the sea.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><br> The <b>Byzantine Bath of the Upper Town</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Βυζαντινά Λουτρά Άνω Πόλης</span>) in <a href="/wiki/Thesaloniki" title="Thesaloniki" class="mw-redirect">Thesaloniki</a> is the only Byzantine bath that has survived from the middle <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Empire" title="Byzantine Empire">Byzantine period</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. It is located on the Theotokopoulou Street in the Upper Old City of Thessaloniki.</p>
            <p>The baths date to the late 13th/early 14th century, and functioned continuously until 1940. The original architecture follows the typical conventions of <a href="/wiki/Roman_baths" title="Roman baths" class="mw-redirect">Roman baths</a>, with a <i><a href="/wiki/Frigidarium" title="Frigidarium">frigidarium</a></i>, <i><a href="/wiki/Tepidarium" title="Tepidarium">tepidarium</a></i> and <i><a href="/wiki/Caldarium" title="Caldarium">caldarium</a></i>, each with two rooms. To the north of the baths was the cistern that provided it with water, with a hearth beneath to warm it. In Byzantine times the building was alternately used by men and women, but in the Ottoman period the bath was divided into exclusively male and female sections, by blocking off each pair of rooms from each other.</p>
            <p>In 1988, it was included among the <a href="/wiki/Paleochristian_and_Byzantine_monuments_of_Thessaloniki" title="Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki">Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki</a> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of the Acheiropoietos</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">[Παναγία] Ἀχειροποίητος</span></span>) is a 5th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>. It is located in the city\'s centre, at Agias Sofias street opposite Makedonomachon square.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>The Acheiropoietos has been dated from its bricks and mosaics to ca. 450–470, making it perhaps the earliest of the city\'s surviving churches. It was modified in the 7th and again in the 14th–15th centuries. Known as the <b><a href="/wiki/Panagia" title="Panagia">Panagia</a> <a href="/wiki/Theotokos" title="Theotokos">Theotokos</a></b> in Byzantine times, it is dedicated to <a href="/wiki/Mary_(mother_of_Jesus)" title="Mary (mother of Jesus)">Mary</a>. Its current name is first attested in 1320, presumably after a miraculous <i><a href="/wiki/Acheiropoieta" title="Acheiropoieta">acheiropoietos</a></i> ("not made by hands") icon of Panagia <a href="/wiki/Hodegetria" title="Hodegetria">Hodegetria</a> that was housed there.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB12_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB12-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Wandering185_3-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Wandering185-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Byzantine sources also indicate that the cult of the city\'s patron saint, <a href="/wiki/St._Demetrius" title="St. Demetrius" class="mw-redirect">St. Demetrius</a>, was also practiced there.<sup id="cite_ref-Wandering185_3-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Wandering185-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The building is a three-<a href="/wiki/Aisle" title="Aisle">aisled</a> <a href="/wiki/Basilica" title="Basilica">basilica</a>, some 28 m wide and 36.5 m long, with a wooden roof. Its eastern end is a semicircular vault, while on the western side a <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a>, flanked by towers, and traces of an exonarthex survive. The three aisles are separated by columns, while the two side aisles have galleries above them. At the eastern end of the northern side aisle, a middle Byzantine <a href="/wiki/Chapel" title="Chapel">chapel</a> dedicated to St. Irene is attached. On the northwestern corner of the basilica, the stairway leading to the galleries survives. The current entrance is through a triple-arched opening (<i>tribelon</i>) that connects the narthex with the main nave, while on the southern side there is a monumental entranceway, which probably connected the church with the city\'s Byzantine-era thoroughfare. Another small adjoining building on the south side has been identified as the church\'s <a href="/wiki/Baptistery" title="Baptistery">baptistery</a>. The modern roof is lower than the original, where the section above the central nave was elevated to allow light in.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB12_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB12-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The surviving parts of the church\'s rich original interior decoration include particularly fine 5th-century <a href="/wiki/Ionic_order" title="Ionic order">Ionian</a> <a href="/wiki/Capital_(architecture)" title="Capital (architecture)">capitals</a> from a <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> workshop, the green Thessalian marble columns of the <i>tribelon</i>, the original <a href="/wiki/Proconnesos" title="Proconnesos" class="mw-redirect">Proconnesian</a> marble pavement of the central nave, and fragments of 5th-century decorative mosaics. Fine but damaged early 13th-century <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">frescoes</a> depicting the <a href="/wiki/Forty_Martyrs_of_Sebaste" title="Forty Martyrs of Sebaste">Forty Martyrs of Sebaste</a> adorn the southern side. Underneath the north aisle\'s current pavement, three kayers floor mosaics from an earlier <a href="/wiki/Roman_bath" title="Roman bath" class="mw-redirect">Roman-era bath</a> have been uncovered.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-5"><span>[</span>5<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>After <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">conquest</a> of the city in 1430, the Acheiropoietos was the first church to be converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a>, by Sultan <a href="/wiki/Murad_II" title="Murad II">Murad II</a> himself. Throughout the Ottoman period, it remained the city\'s principal mosque under the name <b>Eski Camii</b> ("Old Mosque"). An inscription by Murad survives in the northern colonnade, on the eighth column from the east.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Wandering185_3-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Wandering185-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of the Holy Apostles</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">Ἅγιοι Ἀπόστολοι</span></span>) is a 14th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>.</p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>As evidenced by remnants of a column to the south of the church and a cistern to its northwest, it originally formed part of a larger complex. Consequently it appears that the church was originally built as the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of a monastery.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The date of its construction is not entirely clear: the founder\'s inscription above the entrance, the monograms in the <a href="/wiki/Capital_(architecture)" title="Capital (architecture)">capitals</a> and other inscriptions refer to <a href="/wiki/Patriarch_Nephon_I_of_Constantinople" title="Patriarch Nephon I of Constantinople" class="mw-redirect">Nephon I</a>, <a href="/wiki/Patriarch_of_Constantinople" title="Patriarch of Constantinople" class="mw-redirect">Patriarch of Constantinople</a> in 1310–1314, as the <i><a href="/wiki/Ktetor" title="Ktetor">ktetor</a></i>. Another inscription on the eastern wall commemorates the same patriarch and his pupil, the <i><a href="/wiki/Hegumenos" title="Hegumenos" class="mw-redirect">hegumenos</a></i> Paul, as first and second <i>ktetores</i> respectively. Recent analysis using <a href="/wiki/Carbon-14" title="Carbon-14">carbon-14</a> however points to a later date for the entire structure, ca. 1329. A depiction of the <i>hegumenos</i> Paul kneeling before <a href="/wiki/Mary_(mother_of_Jesus)" title="Mary (mother of Jesus)">Mary</a>, as well as a series of Marian scenes lead to the conclusion that the church was dedicated to Mary, perhaps to be identified with the <b>Monastery of Theotokos Gorgoepikoos</b>.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The building belongs to the type of the composite, five-domed <a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a> churches, with four supporting columns. It also features a <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a> with a U-shaped <i>peristoon</i> (an <a href="/wiki/Ambulatory" title="Ambulatory">ambulatory</a> with galleries), with small domes at each corner. There are also two small side-chapels to the east. The exterior walls feature rich decoration with a variety of <a href="/wiki/Brick" title="Brick">brick</a>-work patterns.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The interior gives a very vertical impression, as the ratio of height to width of the church\'s central bay is 5 to 1. The interior decoration consists of rich <a href="/wiki/Mosaic" title="Mosaic">mosaics</a> on the upper levels, inspired by <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> models. These are particularly important as some of the last examples of Byzantine mosaics (and the last of its kind in Thessaloniki itself). <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">Frescoes</a> complete the decoration on the lower levels of the main church, but also on the narthex and one of the chapels. These too show influence from Constantinople, and were possibly executed by a workshop from the imperial capital, perhaps the same which decorated the <a href="/wiki/Chora_Church" title="Chora Church">Chora Church</a>. They were probably carried out under the patronage of the <i>hegumenos</i> Paul, after 1314 or in the period 1328–1334.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>With the <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">conquest</a> of the city by the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Turks" title="Ottoman Turks" class="mw-redirect">Ottoman Turks</a>, in ca. 1520–1530 the church was converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a> with the name <b>Soğuksu Camii</b> ("Mosque of the Cold Water"). As was their usual practice, the Ottomans covered the mosaics and frescoes with plaster, after they removed the gold <i><a href="/wiki/Tesserae" title="Tesserae" class="mw-redirect">tesserae</a></i>. The church\'s modern name, "Holy Apostles", was not attributed to the building until the 19th century.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>Restoration and the gradual revealing of the frescoes began in 1926. After <a href="/wiki/1978_Thessaloniki_earthquake" title="1978 Thessaloniki earthquake">the 1978 earthquake</a>, the building was strengthened, and in 2002, the mosaics were cleaned up.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-6" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Hosios David</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Όσιος Δαβίδ</span>) is a late 5th-century church in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. In <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> times, it functioned as the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of the <b>Latomos Monastery</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el"><span lang="grc" xml:lang="grc">Μονή Λατόμου/Λατόμων</span></span>), and received a rich <a href="/wiki/Mosaic" title="Mosaic">mosaic</a> and <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">fresco</a> decoration, which was renewed in the 12th–14th centuries. The surviving examples are of high artistic quality. Under <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> rule, the building was converted into a mosque (probably in the 16th century), until it was reconsecrated as a <a href="/wiki/Greek_Orthodox" title="Greek Orthodox" class="mw-redirect">Greek Orthodox</a> church in 1921, receiving its present name. In 1988, included among the <a href="/wiki/Paleochristian_and_Byzantine_monuments_of_Thessaloniki" title="Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki">Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki</a> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Panagia Chalkeon</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">Παναγία τῶν Χαλκέων</span></span>) is an 11th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>.</p>

            <h2>Location</h2>
            <p>The church is located at Dikastirion Square, north of the <a href="/wiki/Via_Egnatia" title="Via Egnatia">Via Egnatia</a> at the point where it crosses the Aristotelous Avenue, which leads to the <a href="/wiki/Aristotelous_Square" title="Aristotelous Square">Aristotelous Square</a>. The archaeological site of the city\'s Roman forum is located northeast, while its name, which translates as "the Virgin of the Copper-smiths", derives from its proximity to the area traditionally occupied by the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Coppersmith" title="Coppersmith">coppersmiths</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>According to the founder\'s inscription above the west entrance, the church was built in 1028 by the <i><a href="/wiki/Protospatharios" title="Protospatharios">protospatharios</a></i> Christopher, <i><a href="/wiki/Katepano" title="Katepano">katepano</a></i> of <a href="/wiki/Longobardia" title="Longobardia">Longobardia</a>, and his wife Maria, son Nikephoros and two daughters, Anna and Katakale. Christopher\'s tomb was probably located in an <a href="/wiki/Arcosolium" title="Arcosolium">arcosolium</a> on the church\'s northern wall.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The ground plan is that of a classic "<a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a>-form" typical of <a href="/wiki/Macedonian_dynasty" title="Macedonian dynasty">Macedonian</a>-period architecture, with four columns and three domes, one central and two over the <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a>. The entire building is built of <a href="/wiki/Brick" title="Brick">bricks</a>, which gave it the popular nickname "Red Church" (Κόκκινη Εκκλησιά). The exterior is enlivened with a variety of arches and <a href="/wiki/Pilaster" title="Pilaster">pilasters</a>, elements which can be traced to <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> influence. The use of arches with several <a href="/wiki/Setback_(architecture)" title="Setback (architecture)">setbacks</a> gives the building a "sculpted" appearance. In the interior, most of the carved marble decoration, as well as <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">frescoes</a> from the 11th and 14th centuries have been preserved.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>With the <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">conquest</a> of the city in 1430 by the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Turks" title="Ottoman Turks" class="mw-redirect">Ottoman Turks</a>, the church was turned into a mosque, named <b>Kazancilar Camii</b> ("Mosque of the Cauldron-Merchants").<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Catherine</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Αγία Αικατερίνη</span>) is a late <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northwestern corner of the old city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. The church dates to the <a href="/wiki/Palaiologan_period" title="Palaiologan period" class="mw-redirect">Palaiologan period</a>, but its exact dating and original dedication are unknown. From its interior decoration, which survives in fragments and is dated to ca. 1315, it has been suggested that it was the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of the Monastery of the Almighty. It was converted to a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a> by Yakup Pasha in the reign of the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> sultan <a href="/wiki/Bayezid_II" title="Bayezid II">Bayezid II</a> (r. 1481–1512) and named after him <b>Yakup Pasha Mosque</b> (<a href="/wiki/Turkish_language" title="Turkish language">Turkish</a>: <span lang="tr" xml:lang="tr"><i>Yakup Paşa Camii</i></span>). In 1988, it was included among the <a href="/wiki/Paleochristian_and_Byzantine_monuments_of_Thessaloniki" title="Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki">Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki</a> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Nicholas Orphanos</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">Ἅγιος Νικόλαος ὁ Ὀρφανός</span></span>) is an early 14th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>.</p>

            <h2>Location</h2>
            <p>The church is located in the northeastern corner of the old city, just inside the eastern wall, between the Irodotou and Apostolou Pavlou streets.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>The church\'s name, "Saint Nicholas the Orphan", is first attested in the 17th and 18th centuries, and presumably refers to its otherwise unknown <i><a href="/wiki/Ktetor" title="Ktetor">ktetor</a></i> (founder). From its interior decoration, the building is dated to the period 1310–1320. The church originally formed part of a monastery, traces of which (remnants of a gate) survive to the east.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The church was originally built as a simple, single-aisled edifice with a wooden <a href="/wiki/Gabled_roof" title="Gabled roof" class="mw-redirect">gabled roof</a>. Later, aisles were added on three sides. They form an <a href="/wiki/Ambulatory" title="Ambulatory">ambulatory</a>, under whose floor several graves have been found. The masonry features irregular layers of brick and stone, with a few ceramics on the eastern side and brick decoration on the eastern and western sides. In the interior, the central aisle is connected to the others with double openings decorated with reused <a href="/wiki/Late_antique" title="Late antique" class="mw-redirect">late antique</a> <a href="/wiki/Capital_(architecture)" title="Capital (architecture)">capitals</a>. The church\'s original marble <a href="/wiki/Templon" title="Templon">templon</a> survives.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The church is most notable for its <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">frescoes</a>, contemporary with the church\'s construction, which cover almost the entire interior surface. The frescoes are an example of the Thessalonican school at the height of the "<a href="/wiki/Palaiologan_Renaissance" title="Palaiologan Renaissance" class="mw-redirect">Palaiologan Renaissance</a>", and their creator may be the same who decorated the <a href="/wiki/Hilandar_monastery" title="Hilandar monastery" class="mw-redirect">Hilandar monastery</a> in <a href="/wiki/Mount_Athos" title="Mount Athos">Mount Athos</a> in 1314. The church has been linked to the <a href="/wiki/Medieval_Serbia" title="Medieval Serbia" class="mw-redirect">Serbian</a> king <a href="/wiki/Stephen_Uro%%C5%%A1_II_Milutin_of_Serbia" title="Stephen Uroš II Milutin of Serbia" class="mw-redirect">Stephen Uroš II Milutin</a> (r. 1282–1321), who is known to have sponsored churches in the city, on account of the depiction in the main aisle of St George Gorgos, the Serbian ruler\'s patron saint, and of St. Clemens of Ohrid, a favourite motif of the Serbian churches.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The monastery continued functioning throughout the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> period. The frescoes were uncovered in 1957–1960 during restoration works.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Panteleimon</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el">Ναός Αγίου Παντελεήμονα</span>) is a late <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>, and a <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a> <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Site</a>.</p>
            <p>The church lies in the eastern part of the old city, near the <a href="/wiki/Tomb_of_Galerius" title="Tomb of Galerius" class="mw-redirect">Tomb of Galerius</a> (the "Rotunda"), at the junction of Iasonidou and Arrianou streets. Its current dedication to Saint Panteleimon was given to the church after the end of <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> rule in 1912, and its original dedication is therefore disputed. In Ottoman times, it was converted into a mosque in 1548 and became known as <b>Ishakiye Camii</b> ("Mosque of Ishak [Isaac]"), which in the prevailing scholarly interpretation points to an identification with the late Byzantine <b>Monastery of the Virgin Peribleptos</b>, also known as the <b>Monastery of Kyr Isaac</b> after its <a href="/wiki/Ktetor" title="Ktetor">founder</a> Jacob, who was the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Metropolitan_bishop" title="Metropolitan bishop">metropolitan bishop</a> in 1295–1315 and became a monk with the <a href="/wiki/Monastic_name" title="Monastic name" class="mw-redirect">monastic name</a> of Isaac. A counter-argument however supports the theory that the present church is unrelated to the Peribleptos Monastery, and that it was converted into a mosque ca. 1500, when the city\'s <i><a href="/wiki/Kad%%C4%%B1" title="Kadı">kadı</a></i> (judge), was Ishak Çelebi, whom the mosque was named after. However, the church\'s architecture and decoration, which date to the late 13th/early 14th centuries, appear to support the former view.</p>
            <p>The church is of the tetrastyle <a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a> type, with a <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a> and a (now destroyed) <a href="/wiki/Ambulatory" title="Ambulatory">ambulatory</a> that is connected to two chapels (still extant). Very few of the building\'s original wall paintings survive. Ottoman remains include the base of the demolished minaret and a marble fountain.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Prophet Elijah</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Ναός Προφήτη Ηλία</span>) is a 14th-century church in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>, and a <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a> <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Site</a>.</p>
            <p>The church is located in the upper quarter of the old city, and dates to the <a href="/wiki/Palaiologan_period" title="Palaiologan period" class="mw-redirect">Palaiologan period</a>, but its original dedication is unknown. In <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> times, it was known as the <b>Saraylı Mosque</b>, and through a misinterpretation of this name came about its modern dedication to the Prophet Elijah. It has been traditionally identified as the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of the Nea Moni monastery, built ca. 1360–1370 on the site of a former palace destroyed in 1342 by the <a href="/wiki/Zealots_of_Thessalonica" title="Zealots of Thessalonica">Zealot uprising</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> Modern research however has cast doubt on this, since the Nea Moni continued to operate well into the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> period, while the church of Prophet Elijah was converted into a mosque by Badrah Mustafa Pasha immediately after the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">capture</a> in 1430. On the basis of its internal decoration, it has been suggested that the church was the <i>katholikon</i> of the important Akapniou Monastery.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>Its architectural style, a variant of <a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a> church known as the "<a href="/w/index.php?title=Athonite_type&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Athonite type (page does not exist)">Athonite type</a>", is unique in the city, and was always reserved for <i>katholika</i> of monasteries. The careful masonry, of alternating courses of bricks and white ashlar, is also unusual for Thessaloniki and its region; it is copied from <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> architecture.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Fragments of the church\'s original decoration survive in the form of wall paintings, fine examples of late <a href="/w/index.php?title=Palaiologan_art&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Palaiologan art (page does not exist)">Palaiologan art</a>, which influenced later paintings in <a href="/wiki/Medieval_Serbia" title="Medieval Serbia" class="mw-redirect">Serbia</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Demetrius</b>, or <b>Hagios Demetrios</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Άγιος Δημήτριος</span>), is the main sanctuary dedicated to <a href="/wiki/Demetrius_of_Thessaloniki" title="Demetrius of Thessaloniki">Saint Demetrius</a>, the patron saint of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> (in <a href="/wiki/Central_Macedonia" title="Central Macedonia">Central Macedonia</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>), dating from a time when it was the second largest city of the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Empire" title="Byzantine Empire">Byzantine Empire</a>. It is part of the site <b>Palaeochristian and Byzantine Monuments of Thessaloniki</b> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Sites" title="World Heritage Sites" class="mw-redirect">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/United_Nations_Educational,_Scientific_and_Cultural_Organization" title="United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization" class="mw-redirect">UNESCO</a> since 1988.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The first church on the spot was constructed in the early 4th century AD, replacing a <a href="/wiki/Roman_bath" title="Roman bath" class="mw-redirect">Roman bath</a>. A century later, a prefect named Leontios replaced the small <a href="/wiki/Oratory_(worship)" title="Oratory (worship)">oratory</a> with a larger, three-aisled <a href="/wiki/Basilica" title="Basilica">basilica</a>. Repeatedly gutted by fires, the church eventually was reconstructed as a five-aisled basilica in 629–634. This was the surviving form of the church much as it is today. The most important shrine in the city, it was probably larger than the local cathedral. The historic location of the latter is now unknown.</p>
            <p>The church had an unusual shrine called the <i><a href="/wiki/Ciborium_(architecture)" title="Ciborium (architecture)">ciborium</a></i>, a <a href="/wiki/Hexagonal" title="Hexagonal" class="mw-redirect">hexagonal</a>, roofed structure at one side of the nave. It was made of or covered with silver. The structure had doors and inside was a couch or bed. Unusually, it did not hold any physical relics of the saint. The ciborium seems to have been a symbolic tomb. It was rebuilt at least once.<sup id="cite_ref-RC_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-RC-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The basilica is famous for six extant <a href="/wiki/Mosaic" title="Mosaic">mosaic</a> panels, dated to the period between the latest reconstruction and the inauguration of the <a href="/wiki/Iconoclastic" title="Iconoclastic" class="mw-redirect">Iconoclastic</a> policies in 730. These mosaics, depicting St. Demetrius with officials responsible for the restoration (called the founders) and with children, represent rare examples of art surviving from the <a href="/wiki/Dark_Age" title="Dark Age" class="mw-redirect">Dark Age</a> that followed <a href="/wiki/Justinian" title="Justinian" class="mw-redirect">Justinian</a>\'s death. An inscription below one of the images glorifies heaven for saving the people of Saloniki from a pagan <a href="/wiki/Slavic_peoples" title="Slavic peoples" class="mw-redirect">Slavic</a> raid in 612.</p>
            <p>Other magnificent mosaics, recorded as covering the church interior, were lost either during the four centuries when it functioned as a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a> (1493–1912) or in the <a href="/wiki/Great_Thessaloniki_Fire_of_1917" title="Great Thessaloniki Fire of 1917">Great Thessaloniki Fire of 1917</a> that destroyed much of the city. It also destroyed the roof and upper walls of the church. Black-and-white photographs and good <a href="/wiki/Watercolour" title="Watercolour" class="mw-redirect">watercolour</a> versions give an idea of the early Byzantine craftsmanship lost during the fire.</p>
            <p>Following the Great Fire of 1917, it took decades to restore the church. <a href="/wiki/Archeological" title="Archeological" class="mw-redirect">Archeological</a> excavations conducted in the 1930s and 1940s revealed interesting <a href="/wiki/Artifact_(archaeology)" title="Artifact (archaeology)">artifacts</a> that may be seen in a museum situated inside the church\'s <a href="/wiki/Crypt" title="Crypt">crypt</a>. The excavations also uncovered the ruins of a <a href="/wiki/Roman_bath" title="Roman bath" class="mw-redirect">Roman bath</a>, where St. Demetrius was said to have been held prisoner and executed. A Roman well was also discovered. Scholars believe this is where soldiers dropped the body of St. Demetrius after his execution. After restoration, the church was reconsecrated in 1949.</p>

            <h2>The Crypt</h2>
            <p>Underneath the Church of St Demetrios is the place where St Demetrios, Thessaloniki’s patron saint, was martyred.</p>
            <p>As the level of the ground gradually rose over the centuries, this area acquired the form of a crypt. According both to tradition and to archaeological findings, it was an old bathhouse, in which Demetrios was imprisoned and eventually martyred in ad 303. In the 5th century, when the first Church of St Demetrios was built, the site of his martyrdom was incorporated into the church and the fountain was converted into a source of holy water. In the years that followed, the fountain acquired basins, from which the faithful could collect <i>myron</i>, the sweet-smelling oil produced by the saint’s relics. The crypt filled up with earth during the period of Ottoman rule and was not rediscovered until after the fire of 1917. It has been restored by the Archaeological Service and was converted into an exhibition space in 1988.</p>
            <p>It displays a collection of sculptures, capitals, closure slabs, and vessels from the Church of St Demetrios. More specifically, in room I there are sculptures from the original 5th-century church and piers with relief decoration and capitals with four acanthus leaves. In room II, in the saint’s chapel, there are inscriptions documenting the history of the church, together with figural sculptures of the Middle Byzantine period. Room III displays photographs, plans, and copies of the restoration work done on the church after the fire of 1917.</p>
            <p>In the next room, room IV, there are sculptures from the decoration of the church which was built after the fire in the 7th century, and the ambo from the original 5th-century church is in room V. Rooms VI and VII, lastly, display sculptures from the decoration of the church in the Middle Byzantine period (10th century) and sculptures and pottery of the 13th–15th centuries. More specifically, these include the remains of the original ciborium, which was constructed to house first the saint’s icon and later his sarcophagus. The ciborium was hexagonal and made of wood and silver. There are also an arch and fragments of arches from a Byzantine ciborium over the altar, which latter is ornamented with crosses in medallions and crosses resting on orbs. An inscription indicates that the donor of the ciborium was Theodore, Bishop of Thessaloniki in the 13th century.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Hagia Sophia</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Ἁγία Σοφία</span>, <i>Holy Wisdom</i>) in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>, is one of the oldest churches in that city still standing today. It is one of several monuments in Thessaloniki included as a World Heritage Site on the UNESCO list.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>Since the 3rd century, there was a church in the location of the current Hagia Sophia. In the 8th century, the present structure was erected, based on the <a href="/wiki/Hagia_Sophia" title="Hagia Sophia">Hagia Sophia</a> in <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinople</a> (present-day <a href="/wiki/Istanbul" title="Istanbul">Istanbul</a>, <a href="/wiki/Turkey" title="Turkey">Turkey</a>). In 1205, when the <a href="/wiki/Fourth_Crusade" title="Fourth Crusade">Fourth Crusade</a> captured the city, the Hagia Sophia was converted into the <a href="/wiki/Cathedral" title="Cathedral">cathedral</a> of Thessaloniki, which it remained after the city was returned to the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Empire" title="Byzantine Empire">Byzantine Empire</a> in 1246. After the capture of Thessaloniki by the Ottoman Sultan <a href="/wiki/Murad_II" title="Murad II">Murad II</a> on 29 March 1430, the church was converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-UN_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-UN-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> It was reconverted to a church upon the liberation of Thessaloniki in 1912.</p>
            <p>Its ground plan is that of a <a href="/wiki/Dome" title="Dome">domed</a> <a href="/wiki/Greek_cross" title="Greek cross" class="mw-redirect">Greek cross</a> <a href="/wiki/Basilica" title="Basilica">basilica</a>. Together with the <a href="/wiki/G%%C3%%BCl_Mosque" title="Gül Mosque">Gül</a> and the <a href="/wiki/Kalenderhane_Mosque" title="Kalenderhane Mosque">Kalenderhane Mosques</a> in <a href="/wiki/Istanbul" title="Istanbul">Istanbul</a> and the destroyed Church of the <a href="/wiki/Dormition_of_the_Theotokos" title="Dormition of the Theotokos" class="mw-redirect">Dormition</a> in <a href="/wiki/Iznik" title="Iznik" class="mw-redirect">Nicaea</a>, it represents one of the main architectural examples of this type, typical of the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Architecture" title="Byzantine Architecture" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine middle period</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>In the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Iconoclasm" title="Byzantine Iconoclasm">Iconoclastic</a> era, the <a href="/wiki/Apse" title="Apse">apse</a> of the church was embellished with plain gold <a href="/wiki/Mosaics" title="Mosaics" class="mw-redirect">mosaics</a> with only one great cross, similarly to the <a href="/wiki/Hagia_Irene" title="Hagia Irene">Hagia Irene</a> in Constantinople and the Church of the Dormition in Nicaea. The cross was substituted with the image of the <a href="/wiki/Theotokos" title="Theotokos">Theotokos</a> (God-bearer, or Mary) in 787-797 after the victory of the <a href="/wiki/Iconodules" title="Iconodules" class="mw-redirect">Iconodules</a>. The mosaic in the dome now represents the <a href="/wiki/Ascension_of_Jesus" title="Ascension of Jesus">Ascension</a> with the inscription from <a href="/wiki/Acts_of_the_Apostles" title="Acts of the Apostles">Acts</a> 1:11 "<i>Ye men of Galilee, why stand ye gazing up into heaven?</i>". The dome is ringed by the figures of all <a href="/wiki/Twelve_Apostles" title="Twelve Apostles" class="mw-redirect">Twelve Apostles</a>, <a href="/wiki/Mary_(mother_of_Jesus)" title="Mary (mother of Jesus)">Mary</a> and two angels.</p>
            <p>Between 1907 and 1909 byzantine historian <a href="/wiki/Charles_Diehl" title="Charles Diehl">Charles Diehl</a> restorated the whole building that underwent many damages during a fire in 1890. Much of the interior decoration was plastered over after the <a href="/wiki/Great_Thessaloniki_Fire_of_1917" title="Great Thessaloniki Fire of 1917">Great Thessaloniki Fire of 1917</a>. The dome was not restored until 1980.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Walls of Thessaloniki</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Τείχη της Θεσσαλονίκης</span>) are the <a href="/wiki/City_walls" title="City walls" class="mw-redirect">city walls</a> surrounding the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> during the <a href="/wiki/Middle_Ages" title="Middle Ages">Middle Ages</a> and until the late 19th century, when large parts of the walls, including the entire seaward section, were demolished as part of the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> authorities\' restructuring of Thessaloniki\'s urban fabric. The city was fortified from its establishment in the late 4th century B.O.T, but the present walls date from the early <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> period, ca. 390, and incorporate parts of an earlier, late 3rd-century wall. The walls consist of the typical late Roman mixed construction of <a href="/wiki/Ashlar" title="Ashlar">ashlar</a> masonry alternating with bands of <a href="/wiki/Brick" title="Brick">brick</a>. The northern part of the walls adjoins the <a href="/wiki/Acropolis" title="Acropolis">acropolis</a> of the city, which formed a separate fortified enceinte, and within it lies another citadel, the <a href="/wiki/Heptapyrgion_(Thessaloniki)" title="Heptapyrgion (Thessaloniki)">Heptapyrgion</a> (popularly known by its Ottoman name, Yedi Kule).</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Alaca Imaret Mosque</b> or <b>Ishak Pasha Mosque</b> is a 15th-century <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_architecture" title="Ottoman architecture">Ottoman</a> <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">Mosque</a> in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-Sultan_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Sultan-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>Architecture</h2>
            <p>It was built by order of <a href="/wiki/Ishak_Pasha" title="Ishak Pasha">Ishak Pasha</a> in 1484 or 1487.<sup id="cite_ref-Sultan_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Sultan-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> It consists of a mosque with an <a href="/wiki/Imaret" title="Imaret">imaret</a> (public charity kitchen). The mosque and imaret are not in use anymore. The mosque has a reverse T plan common to early Ottoman architecture, the prayer hall is covered by two large domes, it has a <a href="/wiki/Portico" title="Portico">portico</a> covered by five smaller domes. It had one minaret, which was destroyed after 1912, when Thessaloniki became part of Greece. It is under restoration till now.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Upper Town</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Άνω Πόλη</span>, <i>Ano Poli</i>) is the <a href="/wiki/Old_town" title="Old town">old town</a> of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, located around the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Acropolis" title="Acropolis">acropolis</a>, north of the city center.</p>
            <p>The Upper Town is the most traditional part of the city, as it preserves the Ottoman-era city fabric, otherwise destroyed in the <a href="/wiki/Great_Fire_of_Thessaloniki" title="Great Fire of Thessaloniki" class="mw-redirect">great fire</a> of 1917. Thus it features small stone-paved streets, old squares and houses in traditional Greek and <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_architecture" title="Ottoman architecture">Ottoman architecture</a>. The Upper Town is the highest part of the city, and dominated by the acropolis, the Byzantine and Ottoman-era fort known as <a href="/wiki/Heptapyrgion_(Thessaloniki)" title="Heptapyrgion (Thessaloniki)">Heptapyrgion</a>. The remaining <a href="/wiki/Walls_of_Thessaloniki" title="Walls of Thessaloniki">city walls</a> still ring the Upper Town, with many of its additional Ottoman and Byzantine structures still standing. The <a href="/wiki/Atat%%C3%%BCrk_Museum_(Thessaloniki)" title="Atatürk Museum (Thessaloniki)">Atatürk Museum</a> is also in the Upper Town. During the Ottoman period it was the main district of the Turks of the city, while the Greeks and the Jews were living around the <a href="/wiki/Port_of_Thessaloniki" title="Port of Thessaloniki">port</a>.</p>
            <p>On clear days <a href="/wiki/Mount_Olympus" title="Mount Olympus">Mount Olympus</a>, at about 100&nbsp;km (62&nbsp;mi) away across the gulf, can also be seen towering the horizon.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Bey Hamam</b>, alternatively known as the "Baths of Paradise", is a <a href="/wiki/Turkish_bath" title="Turkish bath">Turkish bathhouse</a> located along <a href="/w/index.php?title=Egnatia_Street&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Egnatia Street (page does not exist)">Egnatia Street</a> in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, east of <a href="/wiki/Panagia_Chalkeon" title="Panagia Chalkeon" class="mw-redirect">Panagia Chalkeon</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>Built in 1444 by sultan <a href="/wiki/Murad_II" title="Murad II">Murad II</a>, it was the first <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> bath in Thessaloniki and the most important one still standing throughout <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. For this reason, it is a part of those few important vestiges of <a href="/wiki/Culture_of_the_Ottoman_Empire" title="Culture of the Ottoman Empire">Ottoman culture</a> remaining in Thessaloniki and Greece in general.</p>
            <p>It is a double bath, with two separate parts for men and women. The male quarters are the most spacious and luxurious, but each one follows the same tripartite plan - a succession of three parts, the cold, tepid, and hot rooms. A large rectangular <a href="/wiki/Cistern" title="Cistern">cistern</a> flanks the baths to the east and guarantees their water supply.</p>
            <p>The baths for the men include a large octagonal cold room, with a gallery resting on columns, arcades surrounding their windows, and a painted cupola. It is followed, in south-east, by the tepid room, also octagonal, equipped with a cupola with occuli and with a rich series of painted depictions of plants. Further to the east lies the complex of hot rooms, ordered around a large cruciform room, wherein the massage table might always be found, standing, now as ever, in its centre. Eight small hot and tepid rooms open on this space and are equipped with basins and marble benches.</p>
            <p>The baths remained in usage, under the name "Baths of Paradise", up until 1968, where they were leased to the Greek archaeological service for four years. After the earthquake of 1978, which shook Thessaloniki especially hard, the baths were restored, and are used to this day for cultural events and short-lived exhibitions. Meanwhile, the eastern annex became the principal shop of the Foundation of Archaeological Receipts of the <a href="/wiki/Hellenic_Republic_Ministry_of_Culture" title="Hellenic Republic Ministry of Culture" class="mw-redirect">Hellenic Republic Ministry of Culture</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Karipeio Melathro</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Καρίπειο Μέλαθρο</span>) is an <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a>-period historical building in the center of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki,_Greece" title="Thessaloniki, Greece" class="mw-redirect">Thessaloniki, Greece</a>. It is located in the crossroad of Olympiados and F. Dragoumi streets.</p>
            <p>Its <a href="/wiki/Architect" title="Architect">architect</a> is the <a href="/wiki/Italian_people" title="Italian people" class="mw-redirect">Italian</a> <a href="/wiki/Vitaliano_Poselli" title="Vitaliano Poselli">Vitaliano Poselli</a>. Karipio was the official residence of the then <a href="/wiki/Selanik" title="Selanik" class="mw-redirect">Selanik</a> Prefect, who was the political representative of the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman Empire</a> in <a href="/wiki/Macedonia_(region)" title="Macedonia (region)">Macedonia</a>. After Thessaloniki became part of Greece in 1912, the building became a property of the <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> State. In a 1980 decision, the <a href="/wiki/Minister_for_Culture_(Greece)" title="Minister for Culture (Greece)" class="mw-redirect">Greek Ministry of Culture</a> put Karipio under the status of its state protection. Today, the 4-stores building is a property of doctor Alexandros Karipis and home to the <a href="/wiki/Non-governmental" title="Non-governmental" class="mw-redirect">non-governmental</a> <a href="/w/index.php?title=Institute_for_National_and_Religious_Studies_(Thessaloniki)&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Institute for National and Religious Studies (Thessaloniki) (page does not exist)">Institute for National and Religious Studies</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Konak</b> (<a href="/wiki/Turkish_language" title="Turkish language">Turkish</a>: <span lang="tr" xml:lang="tr"><i>Konak</i></span>, <a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Κονάκι</span>) or <b>Government House</b> (Διοικητήριο) is an <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a>-era building in central <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. Originally built in 1891 as the residence (<i><a href="/wiki/Konak_(residence)" title="Konak (residence)">konak</a></i>) of the governor-general (<i><a href="/wiki/W%%C4%%81li" title="Wāli" class="mw-redirect">vali</a></i>) of the <a href="/wiki/Salonica_Vilayet" title="Salonica Vilayet">Salonica Vilayet</a> and the seat of the Ottoman authorities, it now houses the <a href="/wiki/Ministry_of_Macedonia_and_Thrace" title="Ministry of Macedonia and Thrace">Ministry of Macedonia and Thrace</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The Konak was built in 1891 by <a href="/wiki/Italy" title="Italy">Italian</a> <a href="/wiki/Architect" title="Architect">architect</a> <a href="/wiki/Vitaliano_Poselli" title="Vitaliano Poselli">Vitaliano Poselli</a>. The architect chose <a href="/wiki/Eclecticism" title="Eclecticism">eclecticism</a> as the main style for the building, which combines elements of various <a href="/wiki/Architectural_styles" title="Architectural styles" class="mw-redirect">architectural styles</a> such as <a href="/wiki/Neoclassicism" title="Neoclassicism">neoclassicism</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> It sits on top of the ruins of the imperial palace of the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Emperor" title="Byzantine Emperor" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine Emperor</a> in Thessaloniki, of which some remnants have been found near the building. When it was completed in the late 1890s, it only had three floors. The fourth floor, in <a href="/wiki/Neoclassical_architecture" title="Neoclassical architecture">neoclassical</a> style, was added in 1955.</p>
            <p>In 1907, the building housed the Ottoman School of Law, and in 1911 the <a href="/wiki/List_of_Ottoman_Sultans" title="List of Ottoman Sultans" class="mw-redirect">Sultan</a> <a href="/wiki/Mehmed_V" title="Mehmed V">Mehmed V Reshad</a> stayed here during his visit to the city. During the <a href="/wiki/First_Balkan_War" title="First Balkan War">First Balkan War</a>, it was inside this building that the documents of the <a href="/wiki/History_of_Thessaloniki#Balkan_Wars_and_World_War_I" title="History of Thessaloniki">surrender of Thessaloniki</a> were signed, making Thessaloniki part of the <a href="/wiki/Kingdom_of_Greece" title="Kingdom of Greece">Kingdom of Greece</a>. From 1912 to 1929 the building housed the Governorate-General of Macedonia. During the <a href="/wiki/Great_Thessaloniki_Fire_of_1917" title="Great Thessaloniki Fire of 1917">fire of 1917</a>, the building sustained no damage, despite widespread devastation in the area, which destroyed much of the old city centre.</p>
            <p>It is a <a href="/wiki/Listed_building" title="Listed building">listed building</a> as "The Government House of Thessaloniki" (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Διοικητήριο Θεσσαλονίκης</span>).</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>New Mosque</b> (<a href="/wiki/Turkish_language" title="Turkish language">Turkish</a>: <span lang="tr" xml:lang="tr"><i>Yeni Camii</i></span>; <a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Γενί Τζαμί</span>, <i>Yeni Tzami</i>) is a historical <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a> in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. It was built by Italian architect <a href="/wiki/Vitaliano_Poselli" title="Vitaliano Poselli">Vitaliano Poselli</a> in 1902 for the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Donmeh" title="Donmeh" class="mw-redirect">Donmeh</a> community, Jewish converts to Islam. However, when the Donmeh left the city during the <a href="/wiki/Population_exchange_between_Greece_and_Turkey" title="Population exchange between Greece and Turkey">population exchange between Greece and Turkey</a>, it was used to house the <a href="/wiki/Archaeological_Museum_of_Thessaloniki" title="Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki">Archaeological Museum of Thessaloniki</a> in 1925.<sup id="cite_ref-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> Today it serves as an exhibition center.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>White Tower of Thessaloniki</b> (<a href="/wiki/Ladino_language" title="Ladino language" class="mw-redirect">Ladino</a>: <span lang="lad" xml:lang="lad"><i>Kuli Blanka</i></span>, <a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Λευκός Πύργος</span> <i>Lefkos Pyrgos</i>, <a href="/wiki/Turkish_language" title="Turkish language">Turkish</a>: <span lang="tr" xml:lang="tr"><i>Beyaz Kule</i></span>) is a monument and museum on the waterfront of the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, capital of the <a href="/wiki/Macedonia_(Greece)" title="Macedonia (Greece)">region of Macedonia</a> in northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. The present tower replaced an old <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_architecture" title="Byzantine architecture">Byzantine</a> <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_military" title="Byzantine military" class="mw-redirect">fortification</a>, known to have been mentioned around the 12th century, that the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman Empire</a> reconstructed to fortify the city\'s harbour sometime after Sultan <a href="/wiki/Murad_II" title="Murad II">Murad II</a> captured Thessaloniki in 1430. The tower became a notorious prison and scene of mass executions during the period of <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_rule_in_Greece" title="Ottoman rule in Greece" class="mw-redirect">Ottoman rule</a>.</p>
            <p>The White Tower was substantially remodeled and its exterior was whitewashed after Greece gained control of the city in 1912. It has been adopted as the symbol of the city.</p>

            <h2>Physical Attributes</h2>
            <p>The White Tower takes the form of a cylindrical drum 23&nbsp;m (75&nbsp;ft) in diameter with a height of 34&nbsp;m (112&nbsp;ft) above ground level, on top of which is a turret 12&nbsp;m (39&nbsp;ft) in diameter and 6&nbsp;m (20&nbsp;ft) high. Some of the <a href="/wiki/Embrasure" title="Embrasure">embrasures</a> in the outer wall of the tower are reached by a spiral ramp; others are accessed from a central room on each of the six floors.</p>
            <p>The turret houses a platform with a diameter of 10&nbsp;m (33&nbsp;ft), and the platform at the top of the main tower in front of the turret is about 5&nbsp;m (16&nbsp;ft) wide.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The tower, which once guarded the eastern end of the city\'s sea walls, was for many years attributed to <a href="/wiki/Republic_of_Venice" title="Republic of Venice">Venice</a>, to which the Byzantines ceded Thessaloniki in 1423. It is now known that the tower was constructed by the Ottomans sometime after the army of Sultan <a href="/wiki/Murad_II" title="Murad II">Murad II</a> captured Thessaloniki in 1430.<sup id="cite_ref-Tracy_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Tracy-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> Until 1912, an inscription in <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Turkish_language" title="Ottoman Turkish language">Ottoman Turkish</a> verse above the door dated the structure to <a href="/wiki/Anno_Hegirae" title="Anno Hegirae" class="mw-redirect">AH</a> 942 (1535–1536).</p>
            <p>The historian <a href="/wiki/Franz_Babinger" title="Franz Babinger">Franz Babinger</a> speculated that the work was designed by the great Ottoman architect <a href="/wiki/Mimar_Sinan" title="Mimar Sinan">Mimar Sinan</a>, who is known to have built fortifications, including a similar tower at the Albanian port <a href="/wiki/Vlor%%C3%%AB" title="Vlorë">Valona</a> in 1537.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h3>Modifications</h3>
            <p>The present tower likely replaced an older <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Empire" title="Byzantine Empire">Byzantine</a> tower mentioned by the 12th-century archbishop <a href="/wiki/Eustathius_of_Thessalonica" title="Eustathius of Thessalonica">Eustathius of Thessalonica</a> during the <a href="/wiki/Sack_of_Thessalonica_(1185)" title="Sack of Thessalonica (1185)">sack of the city in 1185</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The Ottoman-built structure itself has been altered substantially over the years. Early illustrations<sup class="noprint Inline-Template" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Manual_of_Style/Dates_and_numbers#Chronological_items" title="Wikipedia:Manual of Style/Dates and numbers"><span title="The time period mentioned near this tag is ambiguous. (January 2016)">when?</span></a></i>]</sup> show that it was originally covered by a conical roof, like similar towers in the <a href="/wiki/Yedikule_Fortress" title="Yedikule Fortress">Yedikule Fortress</a> and <a href="/wiki/Rumelihisar%%C4%%B1" title="Rumelihisarı">Rumelihisarı</a> fortress in <a href="/wiki/Istanbul" title="Istanbul">Istanbul</a>.</p>
            <p>Until its demolition in 1917, a <i><a href="/wiki/Chemise_(wall)" title="Chemise (wall)">chemise</a></i> stood at the foot of the tower, supporting the heavy guns and enclosing an area at least three times the diameter of the main tower. Octagonal turrets on the <i>chemise</i> and <i><a href="/wiki/Caponier" title="Caponier">caponiers</a></i> at ground level provided flanking fire around the tower. It is unclear whether the <i>chemise</i> was part of the original scheme for the tower or was a later addition.<sup id="cite_ref-Tracy_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Tracy-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The tower was for centuries part of the walls of the old city of Thessaloniki, separating the Jewish quarter of the city from the cemeteries of the Muslims and Jews.<sup id="cite_ref-Glenny.2C_p.181_4-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Glenny.2C_p.181-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup> The city walls were demolished in 1866.</p>

            <h3>From the Red Tower to the White Tower</h3>
            <p>The Tower was used by the Ottomans successively as a fortress, garrison and a prison. In 1826, at the order of the Sultan <a href="/wiki/Mahmud_II" title="Mahmud II">Mahmud II</a>, there was <a href="/wiki/The_Auspicious_Incident" title="The Auspicious Incident" class="mw-redirect">a massacre</a> of the rebellious <a href="/wiki/Janissary" title="Janissary" class="mw-redirect">Janissaries</a> imprisoned there. Owing to the "countless victims of Ottoman torturers and executioners", the tower acquired the name "Tower of Blood" or "Red Tower" (<a href="/wiki/Turkish_language" title="Turkish language">Turkish</a>: <span lang="tr" xml:lang="tr"><i>Kanli Kule</i></span>), a name which it kept until the end of the 19th century.<sup id="cite_ref-Glenny.2C_p.181_4-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Glenny.2C_p.181-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>When Thessaloniki was annexed from the Ottoman Empire to the <a href="/wiki/Hellenic_State" title="Hellenic State">Hellenic State</a> in 1912 during the <a href="/wiki/First_Balkan_War" title="First Balkan War">First Balkan War</a>, the tower was whitewashed as a symbolic gesture of cleansing, and acquired its present name. King <a href="/wiki/George_I_of_Greece" title="George I of Greece">George I of Greece</a> was assassinated not far from the White Tower in March 1913.</p>
            <p>The Tower is now a buff colour but has retained the name White Tower. It now stands on Thessaloniki\'s waterfront boulevard, Nikis (Victory) Street. It houses a museum dedicated to the history of Thessaloniki and is one of the city\'s leading tourist attractions.</p>

            <h2>White Tower Museum</h2>
            <p>The White Tower houses an exhibition dedicated to the city of Thessaloniki and its history throughout various periods, organized by the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Museum_of_Byzantine_Culture" title="Museum of Byzantine Culture">Museum of Byzantine Culture</a>. It is under the administration of the Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities of the <a href="/wiki/Greek_Ministry_of_Culture" title="Greek Ministry of Culture" class="mw-redirect">Greek Ministry of Culture</a>.</p>
            <p>The Tower is open to the public, and visitors have the opportunity to view a map of the city with monuments and museums, a timeline with events relevant to Thessaloniki, scientific articles of distinguished historians and archaeologists, bibliography etc. School excursions may be arranged by contacting the Byzantine Museum.<sup id="cite_ref-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-5"><span>[</span>5<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-6" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-6"><span>[</span>6<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-7" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-7"><span>[</span>7<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h3>2002 exhibit</h3>
            <p>For the first few months of 2002 the White Tower housed ‘Byzantine Hours’, an exhibition devoted to ordinary life in Byzantine times.</p>
            <p>Exhibits on the first floor were part of the thematic unit entitled ‘Professionals in the market place’. To be more precise, there were tools and other objects belonging to goldsmiths, blade-smiths, cobblers, glass-makers and tilers, coins and a model of the city of Thessaloniki market place. The second floor was devoted to journeys and trade. So exhibits included objects and texts related to journeys by sea and overland, fairs, spectacles and pilgrimages.</p>
            <p>The third floor was focused mainly on the presentation of the Byzantine home and what the inside, the decoration, suppers and the neighbourhood were like. One floor above this there was an exhibition of life at home with garments and footwear, cosmetics, perfume and jewellery, personal grooming, and even superstitions. The theme of the top floor was death, covering burial and graves, funerary customs, finds from graves, gravestone inscriptions from cemeteries, even objects and specimens of magic were on display in the show cases on the top floor of the Tower.</p>

        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Alexandreio Melathron</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: Αλεξάνδρειο Μέλαθρον) with its main hall named <i><b>Nick Galis Hall</b></i> (Σάλα Νίκος Γκάλης), and also called <i><b>Palais des Sports</b></i> (Παλαί ντε Σπορ), is an <a href="/wiki/Indoor_arena" title="Indoor arena" class="mw-redirect">indoor sports arena</a> that is located in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. It is mainly used to host <a href="/wiki/Basketball" title="Basketball">basketball</a> and <a href="/wiki/Volleyball" title="Volleyball">volleyball</a> games. The arena has a seating capacity of 5,138<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> for basketball games. The arena hosts the home games of <a href="/wiki/Aris_B.C." title="Aris B.C.">Aris B.C.</a>, member of the <a href="/wiki/Greek_Basket_League" title="Greek Basket League">Greek League</a>.</p>

            <h2>Location</h2>
            <p>The <i>Nikos Galis Hall</i> indoor arena is situated in the city centre of Thessaloniki, in the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki_International_Trade_Fair" title="Thessaloniki International Trade Fair">International trade fare grounds</a>. Bus lines #2, #7, #8, #10, #14, #27, #31, and #58, running along Egnatia avenue stop right in front of the arena.</p>

            <h2>Construction</h2>
            <p>The arena was designed by the architects P. Gianettos, M. Guyon and T. Jeanblock between 1960 and 1962. It was built in 1966. The structure shares two of the architects with the <a href="/wiki/Palais_des_Sports_de_Gerland" title="Palais des Sports de Gerland">Palais des Sports de Gerland</a> in Lyon and has many similarities.</p>
            <p>The building was redeveloped and updated in 2004 in preparation for the <a href="/wiki/Athens_2004_Olympic_Games" title="Athens 2004 Olympic Games" class="mw-redirect">Athens 2004 Olympic Games</a>. The updates involved reconstruction of all the building\'s external and internal areas. Apart from what is directly visible to everybody, other works included new electrics and mechanical, air-conditioning, and audiovisual facilities. New seats, <a href="/wiki/Closed-circuit_television" title="Closed-circuit television">CCTV</a>, and new lighting were also installed.</p>
            <p>These updates unfortunately resulted in a lower capacity (5,138 compared to the previous 6,000) for "Alexandreio" Arena, which reopened its gates in late 2004. The arena was again updated in 2015.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The arena was named after <a href="/wiki/Alexander_the_Great" title="Alexander the Great">Alexander the Great</a>, the ancient king of <a href="/wiki/Macedon" title="Macedon" class="mw-redirect">Macedonia</a>. It is also commonly referred to as the "<i>Palais des Sports</i>" (Sports Palace, in <a href="/wiki/French_language" title="French language">French</a>). Under its former names, the arena was the first and biggest indoor basketball arena built in Greece, and remained the biggest until the year 1985, when the <a href="/wiki/Peace_and_Friendship_Stadium" title="Peace and Friendship Stadium">Peace and Friendship Stadium</a> in <a href="/wiki/Athens" title="Athens">Athens</a> was completed and opened to the public.</p>
            <p>Being part of the Thessaloniki International Trade Fair, the arena also serves for many purposes other than sports. It has hosted many international basketball events and was also the home ground for both "arch-rivals", <a href="/wiki/Aris_B.C." title="Aris B.C.">Aris B.C.</a> and <a href="/wiki/PAOK_B.C." title="PAOK B.C." class="mw-redirect">PAOK B.C.</a> for many years; up until the year 2000, when <a href="/wiki/PAOK_B.C." title="PAOK B.C." class="mw-redirect">PAOK B.C.</a> moved into their own new stadium, the <a href="/wiki/P.A.O.K._Sports_Arena" title="P.A.O.K. Sports Arena">P.A.O.K. Sports Arena</a>.</p>
            <p>On May 8, 2013, at an event honoring the retired former Aris player, <a href="/wiki/Nikos_Galis" title="Nikos Galis">Nikos Galis</a>, the Greek deputy culture minister, <a href="/wiki/Giannis_Ioannidis" title="Giannis Ioannidis">Giannis Ioannidis</a>, announced that the main hall of the arena was to be renamed to "Nikos Galis Hall".<sup id="cite_ref-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Aristotelous Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el">Πλατεία Αριστοτέλους</span>, <small>IPA:&nbsp;</small><span title="Representation in the International Phonetic Alphabet (IPA)" class="IPA"><a href="/wiki/Help:IPA_for_Greek" title="Help:IPA for Greek">[plaˈtia aristoˈtelus]</a></span>, <a href="/wiki/Aristotle" title="Aristotle">Aristotle</a> Square) is the main city square of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a> and is located on Nikis avenue (on the city\'s waterfront), in the city center. It was designed by <a href="/wiki/French_people" title="French people">French</a> <a href="/wiki/Architect" title="Architect">architect</a> <a href="/wiki/Ernest_H%%C3%%A9brard" title="Ernest Hébrard">Ernest Hébrard</a> in 1918, but most of the square was built in the 1950s. Many buildings surrounding the central square have since been renovated and its northern parts were largely restored in the 2000s.<sup id="cite_ref-Monumenta_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Monumenta-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The twelve buildings that make up Aristotelous Square have been listed buildings of the <a href="/wiki/Hellenic_Republic" title="Hellenic Republic" class="mw-redirect">Hellenic Republic</a> since 1950.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The twelve buildings that make up Aristotelous Square have been listed buildings of the <a href="/wiki/Hellenic_Republic" title="Hellenic Republic" class="mw-redirect">Hellenic Republic</a> since 1950.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h3>Before the fire</h3>
            <p>Before the Great Fire of 1917, the city lacked much of what was considered to be \'essential\' in <a href="/wiki/Europe" title="Europe">European</a> architecture.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Under <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> rule, the city grew without the guidance of a general plan for expansion and had narrow streets.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos2_4-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos2-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup> The absence of squares in pre-1917 <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> was addressed by <a href="/wiki/Ernest_H%%C3%%A9brard" title="Ernest Hébrard">Ernest Hébrard</a>, who proposed a number of large squares in the city, including Megalou Alexandrou Square ("Alexander the Great Square"), now Aristotelous Square.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos2_4-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos2-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h3>Designs by Ernest Hébrard</h3>
            <p>Ernest Hébrard envisioned a monumental axis for <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> that stretched from what is now Aristotelous Square on the seafront to <a href="/w/index.php?title=Venizelou_Square&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Venizelou Square (page does not exist)">Venizelou Square</a> and the Roman Forum.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Epta_5-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Epta-5"><span>[</span>5<span>]</span></a></sup> The axis began at Aristotelous Square, which was intended to be named after Alexander the Great. Throughout his plan for Thessaloniki, Hébrard implemented an element that was missing from the pre-1917 architecture of the city: imposing <a href="/wiki/Fa%%C3%%A7ades" title="Façades" class="mw-redirect">façades</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> For the monumental axis, the architect used elements from <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_architecture" title="Byzantine architecture">Byzantine</a> and Western architecture<sup id="cite_ref-Epta_5-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Epta-5"><span>[</span>5<span>]</span></a></sup> rather than <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_architecture" title="Ottoman architecture">Ottoman architecture</a>, to stress the city\'s connection with the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Empire" title="Byzantine Empire">Byzantine Empire</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos2_4-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos2-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup> This style is most evident at Aristotelous Square, with a few building facades implementing some of Hébrard\'s original ideas. Additionally, a statue of <a href="/wiki/Alexander_the_Great" title="Alexander the Great">Alexander the Great</a> was to be placed in the middle of the square.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-6" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>Hébrard designed the monumental axis so that looking uphill from the square one could see the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Walls_of_Thessaloniki" title="Walls of Thessaloniki">Byzantine walls</a> and the Upper Town.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-7" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos2_4-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos2-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Zafiris_6-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Zafiris-6"><span>[</span>6<span>]</span></a></sup> Also visible from the square would be what Hébrard called the <i>Place Civique</i> or Civic Square, which would be the city\'s administrative heart along European lines:<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-8" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos2_4-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos2-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup> it would feature the City Hall on the left, the court houses on the right and a grand triumphant arch leading uphill from the Civic Square. This part of the design was never realized due to a lack of funds,<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-9" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> although following archeological excavations unearthed the ancient Roman agora at the same spot were the Civic Square was planned.</p>
            <p>Since the first concept designs by Hébrard in 1918, his designs for Aristotelous Square were simplified considerably.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-10" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos2_4-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos2-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup> Instead of the original elaborate designs, the façades that were built in the 1950s were much more modest,<sup id="cite_ref-Epta_5-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Epta-5"><span>[</span>5<span>]</span></a></sup> due to the financial situation of the country at the time and the decision of the <a href="/wiki/Eleftherios_Venizelos" title="Eleftherios Venizelos">Venizelos</a> government in 1918 to fund the project from private sources and not the government.<sup id="cite_ref-Gerolympos_3-11" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Gerolympos-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h3>Present day</h3>
            <p>Today, Aristotelous Square is one of the most famous places in all of <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a> and almost synonymous with the city of Thessaloniki itself.<sup id="cite_ref-Monumenta_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Monumenta-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> The square plays an important role in the sociopolitical life not only of the city, but of the wider country as well. Numerous large rallies and political speeches have been organized in Aristotelous Square, such as the rally for Macedonia in 1992 (see further <a href="#Political_activity">below</a>). Additionally the square is used for many cultural events, such as festivals and the annual Christmas and carnival celebrations.<sup id="cite_ref-Angels_7-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Angels-7"><span>[</span>7<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Carnival_8-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Carnival-8"><span>[</span>8<span>]</span></a></sup> It is an important tourist attraction for the city, and the numerous cafes and bars that line up the square make it popular with the younger generations.</p>
            <p>The two quarter-circle sides of the square are occupied by important buildings. On the left is Electra Palace Hotel, which is one of the best five-star hotels in Thessaloniki and on the right is one of the city\'s most famous movie theaters, the Olympion Theatre cinema, site of the annual <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki_International_Film_Festival" title="Thessaloniki International Film Festival">Thessaloniki International Film Festival</a>. It also houses a very popular bar of the same name.<sup id="cite_ref-9" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-9"><span>[</span>9<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h3>Future redevelopment</h3>
            <p>There is no redevelopment currently under consideration, but numerous proposals have been submitted over the past twenty years.<sup id="cite_ref-Papadakis_10-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Papadakis-10"><span>[</span>10<span>]</span></a></sup> When Thessaloniki became the <a href="/wiki/European_capital_of_culture" title="European capital of culture" class="mw-redirect">European capital of culture</a> during 1997, the city council put together an organizing committee for the redevelopment of the waterfront of the city, including the redevelopment of Aristotelous Square. Of the many designs that were presented to the committee, some of them were very radical and others less so.<sup id="cite_ref-Papadakis_10-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Papadakis-10"><span>[</span>10<span>]</span></a></sup> In almost all proposals, there were provisions for a marina or a similar extension of the square onto waterfront, as well as a wheel similar to the <a href="/wiki/London_Eye" title="London Eye">London Eye</a> in <a href="/wiki/London" title="London">London</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-Papadakis_10-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Papadakis-10"><span>[</span>10<span>]</span></a></sup> Up to date, no official redevelopment scheme has been made official. The current mayor of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Yannis_Boutaris" title="Yannis Boutaris" class="mw-redirect">Yannis Boutaris</a>, mentioned in his electoral campaign that Thessaloniki would undergo a major redevelopment to bring it into the 21st century,<sup id="cite_ref-11" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-11"><span>[</span>11<span>]</span></a></sup> but so far no designs or any new announcements have been made public.</p>

        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Ladadika</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Λαδάδικα</span>) is the name of a historic district and a landmark area of the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>
            <p>It locates near the <a href="/wiki/Port_of_Thessaloniki" title="Port of Thessaloniki">Port of Thessaloniki</a> and for centuries was one of the most important market places of the city. Its name came about from the many <a href="/wiki/Olive_oil" title="Olive oil">olive oil</a> shops of the area. Many <a href="/wiki/History_of_the_Jews_of_Thessaloniki" title="History of the Jews of Thessaloniki" class="mw-redirect">Jews of the city</a> were living there, while the so-called "Frankish district", with the French/Italian merchants and residents, was located beside.</p>
            <p>In the years before <a href="/wiki/World_War_I" title="World War I">World War I</a> it came to form the <a href="/wiki/Red-light_district" title="Red-light district">red light district</a>, with the area starting to host many <a href="/wiki/Brothels" title="Brothels" class="mw-redirect">brothels</a>. In 1985, Ladakika was listed as a heritage site by the <a href="/wiki/Ministry_of_Culture_and_Sport_(Greece)" title="Ministry of Culture and Sport (Greece)" class="mw-redirect">Ministry of Culture</a>. Its notable architectural style with 19th century buildings is preserved and protected.</p>
            <p>Nowadays, having undergone <a href="/wiki/Gentrification" title="Gentrification">gentrification</a> in the 1980s, Ladadika forms the entertainment district of the city, hosting bars, nightclubs, restaurants and taverna\'s - in what used to be old oil stores and merchant warehouses, which spill out into a network of pedestrianized streets and small squares.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Modiano Market</b> is an enclosed market in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. It was built between 1922 and 1930, in the center of the city and forms the central point of the city\'s market which encompasses over several blocks. It took its name from the architect <a href="/w/index.php?title=Eli_Modiano&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Eli Modiano (page does not exist)">Eli Modiano</a>, a member of the well known Italian–Jewish Modiano family of the city.</p>
            <p>Inside the market there are <a href="/wiki/Fish_markets" title="Fish markets" class="mw-redirect">fish markets</a>, <a href="/wiki/Butcher" title="Butcher">butcher</a> shops, <a href="/wiki/Taverna" title="Taverna">tavernas</a> and bars. It is a place of social meeting and historical significance for the city.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

    </string-array>
</resources>
