<resources>
    <string name="app_name">ThessApp</string>
    <string name="title_activity_main">Main</string>

    <string-array name="array_markeritems_texts">
        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Arch of Galerius</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Gr.</a>: αψίδα του Γαλερίου) (or <b>Kamara</b>, <a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Gr.</a>:καμάρα) and the <b>Rotunda</b> (ροτόντα) are neighboring early 4th-century monuments in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, in the region of <a href="/wiki/Central_Macedonia" title="Central Macedonia">Central Macedonia</a> in northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. The Rotunda is also known as the <b>Church of Agios Georgios</b> or (in English) the <b><a href="/wiki/Rotunda_(architecture)" title="Rotunda (architecture)">Rotunda</a> of <a href="/wiki/St._George" title="St. George" class="mw-redirect">St. George</a></b>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The 4th-century <a href="/wiki/Roman_Emperor" title="Roman Emperor" class="mw-redirect">Roman Emperor</a> <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> commissioned these two structures as elements of an imperial precinct linked to his Thessaloniki palace. <a href="/wiki/Archeologists" title="Archeologists" class="mw-redirect">Archeologists</a> have found substantial remains of the palace to the southwest.<sup id="cite_ref-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> These three monumental structures were connected by a road that ran through the arch, which rose above the major east-west road of the city.</p>
            <p>At the crux of the major axes of the city, the Arch of Galerius emphasized the power of the emperor and linked the monumental structures with the fabric of 4th-century Thessaloniki. The arch was composed of a masonry core faced with <a href="/wiki/Marble" title="Marble">marble</a> sculptural panels celebrating a victory over the <a href="/wiki/Sassanid_Empire" title="Sassanid Empire" class="mw-redirect">Sassanid Persians</a>. About two-thirds the arch is preserved.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda was a massive circular structure with a masonry core that had an <a href="/wiki/Oculus" title="Oculus">oculus</a> like the <a href="/wiki/Pantheon,_Rome" title="Pantheon, Rome">Pantheon</a> in Rome. It has gone through multiple periods of use and modification as a polytheist temple, a Christian basilica, a Muslim mosque, and again a Christian church (and archaeological site). A minaret is preserved from its use as a mosque, and ancient remains are exposed on its southern side.</p>

            <h2>Location and description of the Arch</h2>
            <p>Arch of Galerius, stands on what is now <i>Egnatia &amp; Dimitrios Gounari Street</i>. The arch was built in 298 to 299 AD and dedicated in 303 AD to celebrate the victory of the <a href="/wiki/Tetrarchy" title="Tetrarchy">tetrarch</a> <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> over the <a href="/wiki/Sassanid_Empire" title="Sassanid Empire" class="mw-redirect">Sassanid Persians</a> and capture of their capital <a href="/wiki/Ctesiphon" title="Ctesiphon">Ctesiphon</a> in 298.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> The structure was an octopylon (eight-pillared gateway) forming a triple arch that was built of a rubble masonry core faced first with brick and then with marble panels with sculptural relief. The central arched opening was 9.7 m wide and 12.5 m high, and the secondary openings on other side were 4.8 m wide and 6.5 m high. The central arch spanned the portion of the <i><a href="/wiki/Via_Egnatia" title="Via Egnatia">Via Egnatia</a></i> (primary Roman road from Dyrrhacium to <a href="/wiki/Byzantium" title="Byzantium">Byzantium</a>) that passed through the city as a <a href="/wiki/Decumanus_Maximus" title="Decumanus Maximus"><i>Decumanus</i></a> (east-west major street). A road connecting the Rotunda (125m northeast) with the Palace complex (235m southwest) passed through the arch along its long axis.</p>
            <p>Only the northwestern three of the eight pillars and parts of the <a href="/wiki/Masonry" title="Masonry">masonry</a> cores of the arches above survive: i.e., the entire eastern side (4 pillars) and the southernmost one of the western pillars are lost.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Extensive consolidation with modern brick has been performed on the exposed masonry cores to protect the monument. The two pillars flanking the central arched passageway retain their sculpted <a href="/wiki/Marble" title="Marble">marble</a> slabs, which depict the wars of Galerius against the Persians in broadly panegyric terms.</p>

            <h3>Sculptural program of the Arch</h3>
            <p>Understanding of the sculptural program of the arch is limited by the loss of the majority of the marble panels, but the remains give an impression of the whole. Four vertically stacked registers of sculpted decoration were carved on each pillar, each separated by elaborate moldings. A label for the <a href="/wiki/Tigris_River" title="Tigris River" class="mw-redirect">Tigris River</a> indicates that there were likely labels on other representations as the builders deemed necessary. Artistic license was taken in the representations, for instance, the Caesar Galerius is shown in personal combat with the Sassanid Shah Narses in one of the panels; although they never met in battle.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> On the arch a mounted Galerius attacks a similarly mounted Narses with a lance as an eagle bearing a victory wreath in its talons approaches Galerius. The Caesar sits securely on his rearing horse, while the Persian king appears nearly unhorsed. Terrified Persians cower under the hooves of the Caesar’s horse in the chaos of battle. The panel expresses the power of the Caesar Galerius.</p>
            <p>The relief of the imperial family conjoined in a sacrifice of thanksgiving owes its distant prototype to the Augustan reliefs on the <i><a href="/wiki/Ara_Pacis" title="Ara Pacis">Ara Pacis</a></i> in Rome.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> Galerius\' wife, Diocletian\'s daughter Valeria, is shown at his side, helping authenticate his connection to his predecessor. Here as elsewhere all the faces have been carefully chiselled off, whether as <i><a href="/wiki/Damnatio_memoriae" title="Damnatio memoriae">damnatio memoriae</a></i> or in later cultural intolerance of images.</p>
            <p>In another panel, the tetrarchs are all arrayed in the toga as a <i>Victoria</i> holds a victory wreath out to the heads of the two <i>Augusti</i>. A third panel celebrates the unity of the <a href="/wiki/Tetrarchy" title="Tetrarchy">tetrarchy</a>, with a depiction of the tetrarchs standing together; the depersonalized manner in which the tetrarchs are portrayed is reminiscent of the schematic statues of the tetrarchs in porphyry at <a href="/wiki/St._Mark%27s_Basilica" title="St. Mark\'s Basilica" class="mw-redirect">St. Mark\'s Basilica</a> in Venice.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> Only Galerius is dressed in armor, and he makes the offering upon the altar.</p>
            <p>What remains of the arch asserts the glory of the tetrarchy and the prominence of Galerius within that system. The arch celebrates the Roman Empire as part of Galerius’ victory over the Sassanid king.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> On the right pictured, is Galerius on his horse in an attack on a Sassanid guard.</p>

            <h2>Rotunda of Galerius</h2>
            <p>The Rotunda of Galerius is 125m northeast of the Arch of Galerius at 40°37\'59.77"N, 22°57\'9.77"E. It is also known (by its consecration and use) as the <a href="/wiki/Church_of_Greece" title="Church of Greece">Greek Orthodox</a> Church of <i><a href="/wiki/Saint_George" title="Saint George">Agios Georgios</a></i>, and is informally called the Church of the Rotunda (or simply <i>The Rotunda</i>). The cylindrical structure was built in 306 AD on the orders of the tetrarch <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a>, who was thought to have intended it to be his <a href="/wiki/Mausoleum" title="Mausoleum">mausoleum</a>. It was more likely intended as a temple; it is not known to what god it would have been dedicated.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda has a diameter of 24.5 m. Its walls are more than 6 m thick, which is why it has withstood Thessaloniki\'s earthquakes. The walls are interrupted by eight rectangular bays, with the south bay forming the entrance. A flat brick dome, 30 m high at the peak, crowns the cylindrical structure. In its original design, the dome of the Rotunda had an <i><a href="/wiki/Oculus" title="Oculus">oculus</a></i>, as does the <a href="/wiki/Pantheon,_Rome" title="Pantheon, Rome">Pantheon</a> in Rome.</p>

            <h3>Uses of the Rotunda</h3>
            <p>After Galerius\'s death in 311, he was buried at <a href="/wiki/Gamzigrad" title="Gamzigrad">Gamzigrad</a> (<a href="/wiki/Felix_Romuliana" title="Felix Romuliana" class="mw-redirect">Felix Romuliana</a>) near <a href="/wiki/Zajecar" title="Zajecar" class="mw-redirect">Zajecar</a>, <a href="/wiki/Serbia" title="Serbia">Serbia</a>. The Rotunda stood empty for several years until the Emperor <a href="/wiki/Constantine_I" title="Constantine I" class="mw-redirect">Constantine I</a> ordered it converted into a Christian church in 326. The church was embellished with very high quality <a href="/wiki/Mosaics" title="Mosaics" class="mw-redirect">mosaics</a>. Only fragments have survived of the original decoration, for example, a band depicting saints with hands raised in prayer, in front of complex architectural fantasies.</p>
            <p>The building was used as a church for over 1,200 years until the city fell to the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottomans</a>. In 1590 it was converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a>, called the Mosque of Suleyman Hortaji Effendi, and a <a href="/wiki/Minaret" title="Minaret">minaret</a> was added to the structure. It was used as a mosque until 1912, when the Greeks captured the city during the <a href="/wiki/Balkan_War" title="Balkan War" class="mw-redirect">Balkan War</a>. Greek Orthodox officials reconsecrated the structure as a church, and they left the minaret. The structure was damaged during an earthquake in 1978 but was subsequently restored. As of 2004<sup class="plainlinks noprint asof-tag update" style="display:none;"><a class="external text" href="//en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arch_of_Galerius_and_Rotunda&amp;action=edit">[update]</a></sup>, the minaret was still being stabilized with scaffolding. The building is now a historical monument under the <a href="/w/index.php?title=Ephorate_of_Byzantine_Antiquities&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities (page does not exist)">Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities</a> of the <a href="/wiki/Greek_Ministry_of_Culture" title="Greek Ministry of Culture" class="mw-redirect">Greek Ministry of Culture</a>, although the Greek Orthodox Church has access to the church for various festivities.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda is the oldest of Thessaloniki\'s churches. Some Greek publications claim it is the oldest Christian church in the world, although there are competitors for that title. It is the most important surviving example of a church from the early Christian period of the Greek-speaking part of the Roman Empire.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Navarinou Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Πλατεία Ναβαρίνου</span>) is a <a href="/wiki/Town_square" title="Town square">square</a> in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The square dates back to the Roman period of the city, with the ruins of the palace of <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> located within it. The square is also the site of <a href="/wiki/Massacre_of_Thessalonica" title="Massacre of Thessalonica">Massacre of Thessalonica</a> which took place during the reign of <a href="/wiki/Theodosius_I" title="Theodosius I">Theodosius I</a>.</p>
            <p>Today it is a popular meeting place, mainly amongst the student population of the city.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <a href="/wiki/Roman_Forum" title="Roman Forum">Roman Forum</a> of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> is the ancient Roman-era <a href="/wiki/Forum_(Roman)" title="Forum (Roman)">forum</a> (or <i>Agora</i>) of the city, located at the upper side of <a href="/wiki/Aristotelous_Square" title="Aristotelous Square">Aristotelous Square</a>.</p>
            <p>It is a large two-terraced forum<sup id="cite_ref-Frommer.27s_Greece_Forum_1_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Frommer.27s_Greece_Forum_1-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> featuring two-storey <a href="/wiki/Stoa" title="Stoa">stoas</a>, dug up by accident in the 1960s. The forum complex also boasts two <a href="/wiki/Roman_baths" title="Roman baths" class="mw-redirect">Roman baths</a>,<sup id="cite_ref-A_Companion_1_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-A_Companion_1-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> one of which has been excavated while the other is buried underneath the city, and a small theater which was also used for <a href="/wiki/Gladiatorial_games" title="Gladiatorial games" class="mw-redirect">gladiatorial games</a>. Although the initial complex was not built in Roman times, it was largely refurbished in the 2nd century.<sup id="cite_ref-A_Companion_1_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-A_Companion_1-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> It is believed that the forum and the theater continued to be used until at least the 6th century.<sup id="cite_ref-From_Early_Roman_3-0" class="reference">
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Agias Sofias Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Πλατεία Αγίας Σοφίας</span>) is a <a href="/wiki/Town_square" title="Town square">square</a> in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The square dates back to the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Greece" title="Byzantine Greece">Byzantine</a> period of the city and took its name from the church of <a href="/wiki/Hagia_Sophia,_Thessaloniki" title="Hagia Sophia, Thessaloniki">Hagia Sophia</a> (<i>Holy Wisdom</i>) located within it. At the time is was also called <i>Skalia</i>. During a fire in 1890, it was heavily damaged but was restored under the supervision of <a href="/wiki/Charles_Diehl" title="Charles Diehl">Charles Diehl</a>, a notable Byzantinist.</p>
            <p>Although not a square today, plans have been released which include the complete redevelopment of the area with a new square and pedestrianized zone to extent from the <a href="/wiki/Church_of_the_Acheiropoietos" title="Church of the Acheiropoietos">Church of the Acheiropoietos</a> to the sea.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

    </string-array>
</resources>
