<resources>
    <string name="app_name">ThessApp</string>
    <string name="title_activity_main">Main</string>

    <string-array name="array_markeritems_texts">
        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Arch of Galerius</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Gr.</a>: αψίδα του Γαλερίου) (or <b>Kamara</b>, <a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Gr.</a>:καμάρα) and the <b>Rotunda</b> (ροτόντα) are neighboring early 4th-century monuments in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, in the region of <a href="/wiki/Central_Macedonia" title="Central Macedonia">Central Macedonia</a> in northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. The Rotunda is also known as the <b>Church of Agios Georgios</b> or (in English) the <b><a href="/wiki/Rotunda_(architecture)" title="Rotunda (architecture)">Rotunda</a> of <a href="/wiki/St._George" title="St. George" class="mw-redirect">St. George</a></b>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The 4th-century <a href="/wiki/Roman_Emperor" title="Roman Emperor" class="mw-redirect">Roman Emperor</a> <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> commissioned these two structures as elements of an imperial precinct linked to his Thessaloniki palace. <a href="/wiki/Archeologists" title="Archeologists" class="mw-redirect">Archeologists</a> have found substantial remains of the palace to the southwest.<sup id="cite_ref-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> These three monumental structures were connected by a road that ran through the arch, which rose above the major east-west road of the city.</p>
            <p>At the crux of the major axes of the city, the Arch of Galerius emphasized the power of the emperor and linked the monumental structures with the fabric of 4th-century Thessaloniki. The arch was composed of a masonry core faced with <a href="/wiki/Marble" title="Marble">marble</a> sculptural panels celebrating a victory over the <a href="/wiki/Sassanid_Empire" title="Sassanid Empire" class="mw-redirect">Sassanid Persians</a>. About two-thirds the arch is preserved.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda was a massive circular structure with a masonry core that had an <a href="/wiki/Oculus" title="Oculus">oculus</a> like the <a href="/wiki/Pantheon,_Rome" title="Pantheon, Rome">Pantheon</a> in Rome. It has gone through multiple periods of use and modification as a polytheist temple, a Christian basilica, a Muslim mosque, and again a Christian church (and archaeological site). A minaret is preserved from its use as a mosque, and ancient remains are exposed on its southern side.</p>

            <h2>Location and description of the Arch</h2>
            <p>Arch of Galerius, stands on what is now <i>Egnatia &amp; Dimitrios Gounari Street</i>. The arch was built in 298 to 299 AD and dedicated in 303 AD to celebrate the victory of the <a href="/wiki/Tetrarchy" title="Tetrarchy">tetrarch</a> <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> over the <a href="/wiki/Sassanid_Empire" title="Sassanid Empire" class="mw-redirect">Sassanid Persians</a> and capture of their capital <a href="/wiki/Ctesiphon" title="Ctesiphon">Ctesiphon</a> in 298.<sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> The structure was an octopylon (eight-pillared gateway) forming a triple arch that was built of a rubble masonry core faced first with brick and then with marble panels with sculptural relief. The central arched opening was 9.7 m wide and 12.5 m high, and the secondary openings on other side were 4.8 m wide and 6.5 m high. The central arch spanned the portion of the <i><a href="/wiki/Via_Egnatia" title="Via Egnatia">Via Egnatia</a></i> (primary Roman road from Dyrrhacium to <a href="/wiki/Byzantium" title="Byzantium">Byzantium</a>) that passed through the city as a <a href="/wiki/Decumanus_Maximus" title="Decumanus Maximus"><i>Decumanus</i></a> (east-west major street). A road connecting the Rotunda (125m northeast) with the Palace complex (235m southwest) passed through the arch along its long axis.</p>
            <p>Only the northwestern three of the eight pillars and parts of the <a href="/wiki/Masonry" title="Masonry">masonry</a> cores of the arches above survive: i.e., the entire eastern side (4 pillars) and the southernmost one of the western pillars are lost.<sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Extensive consolidation with modern brick has been performed on the exposed masonry cores to protect the monument. The two pillars flanking the central arched passageway retain their sculpted <a href="/wiki/Marble" title="Marble">marble</a> slabs, which depict the wars of Galerius against the Persians in broadly panegyric terms.</p>

            <h3>Sculptural program of the Arch</h3>
            <p>Understanding of the sculptural program of the arch is limited by the loss of the majority of the marble panels, but the remains give an impression of the whole. Four vertically stacked registers of sculpted decoration were carved on each pillar, each separated by elaborate moldings. A label for the <a href="/wiki/Tigris_River" title="Tigris River" class="mw-redirect">Tigris River</a> indicates that there were likely labels on other representations as the builders deemed necessary. Artistic license was taken in the representations, for instance, the Caesar Galerius is shown in personal combat with the Sassanid Shah Narses in one of the panels; although they never met in battle.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> On the arch a mounted Galerius attacks a similarly mounted Narses with a lance as an eagle bearing a victory wreath in its talons approaches Galerius. The Caesar sits securely on his rearing horse, while the Persian king appears nearly unhorsed. Terrified Persians cower under the hooves of the Caesar’s horse in the chaos of battle. The panel expresses the power of the Caesar Galerius.</p>
            <p>The relief of the imperial family conjoined in a sacrifice of thanksgiving owes its distant prototype to the Augustan reliefs on the <i><a href="/wiki/Ara_Pacis" title="Ara Pacis">Ara Pacis</a></i> in Rome.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> Galerius\' wife, Diocletian\'s daughter Valeria, is shown at his side, helping authenticate his connection to his predecessor. Here as elsewhere all the faces have been carefully chiselled off, whether as <i><a href="/wiki/Damnatio_memoriae" title="Damnatio memoriae">damnatio memoriae</a></i> or in later cultural intolerance of images.</p>
            <p>In another panel, the tetrarchs are all arrayed in the toga as a <i>Victoria</i> holds a victory wreath out to the heads of the two <i>Augusti</i>. A third panel celebrates the unity of the <a href="/wiki/Tetrarchy" title="Tetrarchy">tetrarchy</a>, with a depiction of the tetrarchs standing together; the depersonalized manner in which the tetrarchs are portrayed is reminiscent of the schematic statues of the tetrarchs in porphyry at <a href="/wiki/St._Mark%27s_Basilica" title="St. Mark\'s Basilica" class="mw-redirect">St. Mark\'s Basilica</a> in Venice.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> Only Galerius is dressed in armor, and he makes the offering upon the altar.</p>
            <p>What remains of the arch asserts the glory of the tetrarchy and the prominence of Galerius within that system. The arch celebrates the Roman Empire as part of Galerius’ victory over the Sassanid king.<sup class="noprint Inline-Template Template-Fact" style="white-space:nowrap;">[<i><a href="/wiki/Wikipedia:Citation_needed" title="Wikipedia:Citation needed"><span title="This claim needs references to reliable sources. (December 2010)">citation needed</span></a></i>]</sup> On the right pictured, is Galerius on his horse in an attack on a Sassanid guard.</p>

            <h2>Rotunda of Galerius</h2>
            <p>The Rotunda of Galerius is 125m northeast of the Arch of Galerius at 40°37\'59.77"N, 22°57\'9.77"E. It is also known (by its consecration and use) as the <a href="/wiki/Church_of_Greece" title="Church of Greece">Greek Orthodox</a> Church of <i><a href="/wiki/Saint_George" title="Saint George">Agios Georgios</a></i>, and is informally called the Church of the Rotunda (or simply <i>The Rotunda</i>). The cylindrical structure was built in 306 AD on the orders of the tetrarch <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a>, who was thought to have intended it to be his <a href="/wiki/Mausoleum" title="Mausoleum">mausoleum</a>. It was more likely intended as a temple; it is not known to what god it would have been dedicated.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda has a diameter of 24.5 m. Its walls are more than 6 m thick, which is why it has withstood Thessaloniki\'s earthquakes. The walls are interrupted by eight rectangular bays, with the south bay forming the entrance. A flat brick dome, 30 m high at the peak, crowns the cylindrical structure. In its original design, the dome of the Rotunda had an <i><a href="/wiki/Oculus" title="Oculus">oculus</a></i>, as does the <a href="/wiki/Pantheon,_Rome" title="Pantheon, Rome">Pantheon</a> in Rome.</p>

            <h3>Uses of the Rotunda</h3>
            <p>After Galerius\'s death in 311, he was buried at <a href="/wiki/Gamzigrad" title="Gamzigrad">Gamzigrad</a> (<a href="/wiki/Felix_Romuliana" title="Felix Romuliana" class="mw-redirect">Felix Romuliana</a>) near <a href="/wiki/Zajecar" title="Zajecar" class="mw-redirect">Zajecar</a>, <a href="/wiki/Serbia" title="Serbia">Serbia</a>. The Rotunda stood empty for several years until the Emperor <a href="/wiki/Constantine_I" title="Constantine I" class="mw-redirect">Constantine I</a> ordered it converted into a Christian church in 326. The church was embellished with very high quality <a href="/wiki/Mosaics" title="Mosaics" class="mw-redirect">mosaics</a>. Only fragments have survived of the original decoration, for example, a band depicting saints with hands raised in prayer, in front of complex architectural fantasies.</p>
            <p>The building was used as a church for over 1,200 years until the city fell to the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottomans</a>. In 1590 it was converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a>, called the Mosque of Suleyman Hortaji Effendi, and a <a href="/wiki/Minaret" title="Minaret">minaret</a> was added to the structure. It was used as a mosque until 1912, when the Greeks captured the city during the <a href="/wiki/Balkan_War" title="Balkan War" class="mw-redirect">Balkan War</a>. Greek Orthodox officials reconsecrated the structure as a church, and they left the minaret. The structure was damaged during an earthquake in 1978 but was subsequently restored. As of 2004<sup class="plainlinks noprint asof-tag update" style="display:none;"><a class="external text" href="//en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Arch_of_Galerius_and_Rotunda&amp;action=edit">[update]</a></sup>, the minaret was still being stabilized with scaffolding. The building is now a historical monument under the <a href="/w/index.php?title=Ephorate_of_Byzantine_Antiquities&amp;action=edit&amp;redlink=1" class="new" title="Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities (page does not exist)">Ephorate of Byzantine Antiquities</a> of the <a href="/wiki/Greek_Ministry_of_Culture" title="Greek Ministry of Culture" class="mw-redirect">Greek Ministry of Culture</a>, although the Greek Orthodox Church has access to the church for various festivities.</p>
            <p>The Rotunda is the oldest of Thessaloniki\'s churches. Some Greek publications claim it is the oldest Christian church in the world, although there are competitors for that title. It is the most important surviving example of a church from the early Christian period of the Greek-speaking part of the Roman Empire.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Navarinou Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Πλατεία Ναβαρίνου</span>) is a <a href="/wiki/Town_square" title="Town square">square</a> in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The square dates back to the Roman period of the city, with the ruins of the palace of <a href="/wiki/Galerius" title="Galerius">Galerius</a> located within it. The square is also the site of <a href="/wiki/Massacre_of_Thessalonica" title="Massacre of Thessalonica">Massacre of Thessalonica</a> which took place during the reign of <a href="/wiki/Theodosius_I" title="Theodosius I">Theodosius I</a>.</p>
            <p>Today it is a popular meeting place, mainly amongst the student population of the city.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <a href="/wiki/Roman_Forum" title="Roman Forum">Roman Forum</a> of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> is the ancient Roman-era <a href="/wiki/Forum_(Roman)" title="Forum (Roman)">forum</a> (or <i>Agora</i>) of the city, located at the upper side of <a href="/wiki/Aristotelous_Square" title="Aristotelous Square">Aristotelous Square</a>.</p>
            <p>It is a large two-terraced forum<sup id="cite_ref-Frommer.27s_Greece_Forum_1_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Frommer.27s_Greece_Forum_1-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup> featuring two-storey <a href="/wiki/Stoa" title="Stoa">stoas</a>, dug up by accident in the 1960s. The forum complex also boasts two <a href="/wiki/Roman_baths" title="Roman baths" class="mw-redirect">Roman baths</a>,<sup id="cite_ref-A_Companion_1_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-A_Companion_1-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> one of which has been excavated while the other is buried underneath the city, and a small theater which was also used for <a href="/wiki/Gladiatorial_games" title="Gladiatorial games" class="mw-redirect">gladiatorial games</a>. Although the initial complex was not built in Roman times, it was largely refurbished in the 2nd century.<sup id="cite_ref-A_Companion_1_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-A_Companion_1-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup> It is believed that the forum and the theater continued to be used until at least the 6th century.<sup id="cite_ref-From_Early_Roman_3-0" class="reference">
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><b>Agias Sofias Square</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Πλατεία Αγίας Σοφίας</span>) is a <a href="/wiki/Town_square" title="Town square">square</a> in the city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>.</p>

            <h2>History</h2>
            <p>The square dates back to the <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Greece" title="Byzantine Greece">Byzantine</a> period of the city and took its name from the church of <a href="/wiki/Hagia_Sophia,_Thessaloniki" title="Hagia Sophia, Thessaloniki">Hagia Sophia</a> (<i>Holy Wisdom</i>) located within it. At the time is was also called <i>Skalia</i>. During a fire in 1890, it was heavily damaged but was restored under the supervision of <a href="/wiki/Charles_Diehl" title="Charles Diehl">Charles Diehl</a>, a notable Byzantinist.</p>
            <p>Although not a square today, plans have been released which include the complete redevelopment of the area with a new square and pedestrianized zone to extent from the <a href="/wiki/Church_of_the_Acheiropoietos" title="Church of the Acheiropoietos">Church of the Acheiropoietos</a> to the sea.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p><br> The <b>Byzantine Bath of the Upper Town</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Βυζαντινά Λουτρά Άνω Πόλης</span>) in <a href="/wiki/Thesaloniki" title="Thesaloniki" class="mw-redirect">Thesaloniki</a> is the only Byzantine bath that has survived from the middle <a href="/wiki/Byzantine_Empire" title="Byzantine Empire">Byzantine period</a> in <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. It is located on the Theotokopoulou Street in the Upper Old City of Thessaloniki.</p>
            <p>The baths date to the late 13th/early 14th century, and functioned continuously until 1940. The original architecture follows the typical conventions of <a href="/wiki/Roman_baths" title="Roman baths" class="mw-redirect">Roman baths</a>, with a <i><a href="/wiki/Frigidarium" title="Frigidarium">frigidarium</a></i>, <i><a href="/wiki/Tepidarium" title="Tepidarium">tepidarium</a></i> and <i><a href="/wiki/Caldarium" title="Caldarium">caldarium</a></i>, each with two rooms. To the north of the baths was the cistern that provided it with water, with a hearth beneath to warm it. In Byzantine times the building was alternately used by men and women, but in the Ottoman period the bath was divided into exclusively male and female sections, by blocking off each pair of rooms from each other.</p>
            <p>In 1988, it was included among the <a href="/wiki/Paleochristian_and_Byzantine_monuments_of_Thessaloniki" title="Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki">Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki</a> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of the Acheiropoietos</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">[Παναγία] Ἀχειροποίητος</span></span>) is a 5th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>. It is located in the city\'s centre, at Agias Sofias street opposite Makedonomachon square.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>The Acheiropoietos has been dated from its bricks and mosaics to ca. 450–470, making it perhaps the earliest of the city\'s surviving churches. It was modified in the 7th and again in the 14th–15th centuries. Known as the <b><a href="/wiki/Panagia" title="Panagia">Panagia</a> <a href="/wiki/Theotokos" title="Theotokos">Theotokos</a></b> in Byzantine times, it is dedicated to <a href="/wiki/Mary_(mother_of_Jesus)" title="Mary (mother of Jesus)">Mary</a>. Its current name is first attested in 1320, presumably after a miraculous <i><a href="/wiki/Acheiropoieta" title="Acheiropoieta">acheiropoietos</a></i> ("not made by hands") icon of Panagia <a href="/wiki/Hodegetria" title="Hodegetria">Hodegetria</a> that was housed there.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB12_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB12-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Wandering185_3-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Wandering185-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup> Byzantine sources also indicate that the cult of the city\'s patron saint, <a href="/wiki/St._Demetrius" title="St. Demetrius" class="mw-redirect">St. Demetrius</a>, was also practiced there.<sup id="cite_ref-Wandering185_3-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Wandering185-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The building is a three-<a href="/wiki/Aisle" title="Aisle">aisled</a> <a href="/wiki/Basilica" title="Basilica">basilica</a>, some 28 m wide and 36.5 m long, with a wooden roof. Its eastern end is a semicircular vault, while on the western side a <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a>, flanked by towers, and traces of an exonarthex survive. The three aisles are separated by columns, while the two side aisles have galleries above them. At the eastern end of the northern side aisle, a middle Byzantine <a href="/wiki/Chapel" title="Chapel">chapel</a> dedicated to St. Irene is attached. On the northwestern corner of the basilica, the stairway leading to the galleries survives. The current entrance is through a triple-arched opening (<i>tribelon</i>) that connects the narthex with the main nave, while on the southern side there is a monumental entranceway, which probably connected the church with the city\'s Byzantine-era thoroughfare. Another small adjoining building on the south side has been identified as the church\'s <a href="/wiki/Baptistery" title="Baptistery">baptistery</a>. The modern roof is lower than the original, where the section above the central nave was elevated to allow light in.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB12_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB12-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The surviving parts of the church\'s rich original interior decoration include particularly fine 5th-century <a href="/wiki/Ionic_order" title="Ionic order">Ionian</a> <a href="/wiki/Capital_(architecture)" title="Capital (architecture)">capitals</a> from a <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> workshop, the green Thessalian marble columns of the <i>tribelon</i>, the original <a href="/wiki/Proconnesos" title="Proconnesos" class="mw-redirect">Proconnesian</a> marble pavement of the central nave, and fragments of 5th-century decorative mosaics. Fine but damaged early 13th-century <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">frescoes</a> depicting the <a href="/wiki/Forty_Martyrs_of_Sebaste" title="Forty Martyrs of Sebaste">Forty Martyrs of Sebaste</a> adorn the southern side. Underneath the north aisle\'s current pavement, three kayers floor mosaics from an earlier <a href="/wiki/Roman_bath" title="Roman bath" class="mw-redirect">Roman-era bath</a> have been uncovered.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-5"><span>[</span>5<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>After <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">conquest</a> of the city in 1430, the Acheiropoietos was the first church to be converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a>, by Sultan <a href="/wiki/Murad_II" title="Murad II">Murad II</a> himself. Throughout the Ottoman period, it remained the city\'s principal mosque under the name <b>Eski Camii</b> ("Old Mosque"). An inscription by Murad survives in the northern colonnade, on the eighth column from the east.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-Wandering185_3-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Wandering185-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of the Holy Apostles</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">Ἅγιοι Ἀπόστολοι</span></span>) is a 14th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>.</p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>As evidenced by remnants of a column to the south of the church and a cistern to its northwest, it originally formed part of a larger complex. Consequently it appears that the church was originally built as the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of a monastery.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The date of its construction is not entirely clear: the founder\'s inscription above the entrance, the monograms in the <a href="/wiki/Capital_(architecture)" title="Capital (architecture)">capitals</a> and other inscriptions refer to <a href="/wiki/Patriarch_Nephon_I_of_Constantinople" title="Patriarch Nephon I of Constantinople" class="mw-redirect">Nephon I</a>, <a href="/wiki/Patriarch_of_Constantinople" title="Patriarch of Constantinople" class="mw-redirect">Patriarch of Constantinople</a> in 1310–1314, as the <i><a href="/wiki/Ktetor" title="Ktetor">ktetor</a></i>. Another inscription on the eastern wall commemorates the same patriarch and his pupil, the <i><a href="/wiki/Hegumenos" title="Hegumenos" class="mw-redirect">hegumenos</a></i> Paul, as first and second <i>ktetores</i> respectively. Recent analysis using <a href="/wiki/Carbon-14" title="Carbon-14">carbon-14</a> however points to a later date for the entire structure, ca. 1329. A depiction of the <i>hegumenos</i> Paul kneeling before <a href="/wiki/Mary_(mother_of_Jesus)" title="Mary (mother of Jesus)">Mary</a>, as well as a series of Marian scenes lead to the conclusion that the church was dedicated to Mary, perhaps to be identified with the <b>Monastery of Theotokos Gorgoepikoos</b>.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The building belongs to the type of the composite, five-domed <a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a> churches, with four supporting columns. It also features a <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a> with a U-shaped <i>peristoon</i> (an <a href="/wiki/Ambulatory" title="Ambulatory">ambulatory</a> with galleries), with small domes at each corner. There are also two small side-chapels to the east. The exterior walls feature rich decoration with a variety of <a href="/wiki/Brick" title="Brick">brick</a>-work patterns.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The interior gives a very vertical impression, as the ratio of height to width of the church\'s central bay is 5 to 1. The interior decoration consists of rich <a href="/wiki/Mosaic" title="Mosaic">mosaics</a> on the upper levels, inspired by <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> models. These are particularly important as some of the last examples of Byzantine mosaics (and the last of its kind in Thessaloniki itself). <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">Frescoes</a> complete the decoration on the lower levels of the main church, but also on the narthex and one of the chapels. These too show influence from Constantinople, and were possibly executed by a workshop from the imperial capital, perhaps the same which decorated the <a href="/wiki/Chora_Church" title="Chora Church">Chora Church</a>. They were probably carried out under the patronage of the <i>hegumenos</i> Paul, after 1314 or in the period 1328–1334.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-4"><span>[</span>4<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>With the <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">conquest</a> of the city by the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Turks" title="Ottoman Turks" class="mw-redirect">Ottoman Turks</a>, in ca. 1520–1530 the church was converted into a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a> with the name <b>Soğuksu Camii</b> ("Mosque of the Cold Water"). As was their usual practice, the Ottomans covered the mosaics and frescoes with plaster, after they removed the gold <i><a href="/wiki/Tesserae" title="Tesserae" class="mw-redirect">tesserae</a></i>. The church\'s modern name, "Holy Apostles", was not attributed to the building until the 19th century.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-5" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>Restoration and the gradual revealing of the frescoes began in 1926. After <a href="/wiki/1978_Thessaloniki_earthquake" title="1978 Thessaloniki earthquake">the 1978 earthquake</a>, the building was strengthened, and in 2002, the mosaics were cleaned up.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-6" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Hosios David</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Όσιος Δαβίδ</span>) is a late 5th-century church in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. In <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> times, it functioned as the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of the <b>Latomos Monastery</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el"><span lang="grc" xml:lang="grc">Μονή Λατόμου/Λατόμων</span></span>), and received a rich <a href="/wiki/Mosaic" title="Mosaic">mosaic</a> and <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">fresco</a> decoration, which was renewed in the 12th–14th centuries. The surviving examples are of high artistic quality. Under <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> rule, the building was converted into a mosque (probably in the 16th century), until it was reconsecrated as a <a href="/wiki/Greek_Orthodox" title="Greek Orthodox" class="mw-redirect">Greek Orthodox</a> church in 1921, receiving its present name. In 1988, included among the <a href="/wiki/Paleochristian_and_Byzantine_monuments_of_Thessaloniki" title="Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki">Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki</a> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Panagia Chalkeon</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">Παναγία τῶν Χαλκέων</span></span>) is an 11th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>.</p>

            <h2>Location</h2>
            <p>The church is located at Dikastirion Square, north of the <a href="/wiki/Via_Egnatia" title="Via Egnatia">Via Egnatia</a> at the point where it crosses the Aristotelous Avenue, which leads to the <a href="/wiki/Aristotelous_Square" title="Aristotelous Square">Aristotelous Square</a>. The archaeological site of the city\'s Roman forum is located northeast, while its name, which translates as "the Virgin of the Copper-smiths", derives from its proximity to the area traditionally occupied by the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Coppersmith" title="Coppersmith">coppersmiths</a>.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>According to the founder\'s inscription above the west entrance, the church was built in 1028 by the <i><a href="/wiki/Protospatharios" title="Protospatharios">protospatharios</a></i> Christopher, <i><a href="/wiki/Katepano" title="Katepano">katepano</a></i> of <a href="/wiki/Longobardia" title="Longobardia">Longobardia</a>, and his wife Maria, son Nikephoros and two daughters, Anna and Katakale. Christopher\'s tomb was probably located in an <a href="/wiki/Arcosolium" title="Arcosolium">arcosolium</a> on the church\'s northern wall.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The ground plan is that of a classic "<a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a>-form" typical of <a href="/wiki/Macedonian_dynasty" title="Macedonian dynasty">Macedonian</a>-period architecture, with four columns and three domes, one central and two over the <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a>. The entire building is built of <a href="/wiki/Brick" title="Brick">bricks</a>, which gave it the popular nickname "Red Church" (Κόκκινη Εκκλησιά). The exterior is enlivened with a variety of arches and <a href="/wiki/Pilaster" title="Pilaster">pilasters</a>, elements which can be traced to <a href="/wiki/Constantinople" title="Constantinople">Constantinopolitan</a> influence. The use of arches with several <a href="/wiki/Setback_(architecture)" title="Setback (architecture)">setbacks</a> gives the building a "sculpted" appearance. In the interior, most of the carved marble decoration, as well as <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">frescoes</a> from the 11th and 14th centuries have been preserved.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>With the <a href="/wiki/Siege_of_Thessalonica_(1422%%E2%%80%%931430)" title="Siege of Thessalonica (1422–1430)" class="mw-redirect">conquest</a> of the city in 1430 by the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Turks" title="Ottoman Turks" class="mw-redirect">Ottoman Turks</a>, the church was turned into a mosque, named <b>Kazancilar Camii</b> ("Mosque of the Cauldron-Merchants").<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Catherine</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el" xml:lang="el">Αγία Αικατερίνη</span>) is a late <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northwestern corner of the old city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>. The church dates to the <a href="/wiki/Palaiologan_period" title="Palaiologan period" class="mw-redirect">Palaiologan period</a>, but its exact dating and original dedication are unknown. From its interior decoration, which survives in fragments and is dated to ca. 1315, it has been suggested that it was the <i><a href="/wiki/Katholikon" title="Katholikon">katholikon</a></i> of the Monastery of the Almighty. It was converted to a <a href="/wiki/Mosque" title="Mosque">mosque</a> by Yakup Pasha in the reign of the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> sultan <a href="/wiki/Bayezid_II" title="Bayezid II">Bayezid II</a> (r. 1481–1512) and named after him <b>Yakup Pasha Mosque</b> (<a href="/wiki/Turkish_language" title="Turkish language">Turkish</a>: <span lang="tr" xml:lang="tr"><i>Yakup Paşa Camii</i></span>). In 1988, it was included among the <a href="/wiki/Paleochristian_and_Byzantine_monuments_of_Thessaloniki" title="Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki">Paleochristian and Byzantine monuments of Thessaloniki</a> on the list of <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Sites</a> by <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a>.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Nicholas Orphanos</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el"><span lang="grc">Ἅγιος Νικόλαος ὁ Ὀρφανός</span></span>) is an early 14th-century <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in the northern <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greek</a> city of <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>.</p>

            <h2>Location</h2>
            <p>The church is located in the northeastern corner of the old city, just inside the eastern wall, between the Irodotou and Apostolou Pavlou streets.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>

            <h2>History and description</h2>
            <p>The church\'s name, "Saint Nicholas the Orphan", is first attested in the 17th and 18th centuries, and presumably refers to its otherwise unknown <i><a href="/wiki/Ktetor" title="Ktetor">ktetor</a></i> (founder). From its interior decoration, the building is dated to the period 1310–1320. The church originally formed part of a monastery, traces of which (remnants of a gate) survive to the east.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-0" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The church was originally built as a simple, single-aisled edifice with a wooden <a href="/wiki/Gabled_roof" title="Gabled roof" class="mw-redirect">gabled roof</a>. Later, aisles were added on three sides. They form an <a href="/wiki/Ambulatory" title="Ambulatory">ambulatory</a>, under whose floor several graves have been found. The masonry features irregular layers of brick and stone, with a few ceramics on the eastern side and brick decoration on the eastern and western sides. In the interior, the central aisle is connected to the others with double openings decorated with reused <a href="/wiki/Late_antique" title="Late antique" class="mw-redirect">late antique</a> <a href="/wiki/Capital_(architecture)" title="Capital (architecture)">capitals</a>. The church\'s original marble <a href="/wiki/Templon" title="Templon">templon</a> survives.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-2" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-ODB_2-1" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-ODB-2"><span>[</span>2<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The church is most notable for its <a href="/wiki/Fresco" title="Fresco">frescoes</a>, contemporary with the church\'s construction, which cover almost the entire interior surface. The frescoes are an example of the Thessalonican school at the height of the "<a href="/wiki/Palaiologan_Renaissance" title="Palaiologan Renaissance" class="mw-redirect">Palaiologan Renaissance</a>", and their creator may be the same who decorated the <a href="/wiki/Hilandar_monastery" title="Hilandar monastery" class="mw-redirect">Hilandar monastery</a> in <a href="/wiki/Mount_Athos" title="Mount Athos">Mount Athos</a> in 1314. The church has been linked to the <a href="/wiki/Medieval_Serbia" title="Medieval Serbia" class="mw-redirect">Serbian</a> king <a href="/wiki/Stephen_Uro%%C5%%A1_II_Milutin_of_Serbia" title="Stephen Uroš II Milutin of Serbia" class="mw-redirect">Stephen Uroš II Milutin</a> (r. 1282–1321), who is known to have sponsored churches in the city, on account of the depiction in the main aisle of St George Gorgos, the Serbian ruler\'s patron saint, and of St. Clemens of Ohrid, a favourite motif of the Serbian churches.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup><sup id="cite_ref-3" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-3"><span>[</span>3<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
            <p>The monastery continued functioning throughout the <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> period. The frescoes were uncovered in 1957–1960 during restoration works.<sup id="cite_ref-Ministry_1-4" class="reference"><a href="#cite_note-Ministry-1"><span>[</span>1<span>]</span></a></sup></p>
        ]]>
        </item>

        <item>
        <![CDATA[
            <p>The <b>Church of Saint Panteleimon</b> (<a href="/wiki/Greek_language" title="Greek language">Greek</a>: <span lang="el">Ναός Αγίου Παντελεήμονα</span>) is a late <a href="/wiki/Byzantine" title="Byzantine" class="mw-redirect">Byzantine</a> church in <a href="/wiki/Thessaloniki" title="Thessaloniki">Thessaloniki</a>, <a href="/wiki/Greece" title="Greece">Greece</a>, and a <a href="/wiki/UNESCO" title="UNESCO">UNESCO</a> <a href="/wiki/World_Heritage_Site" title="World Heritage Site">World Heritage Site</a>.</p>
            <p>The church lies in the eastern part of the old city, near the <a href="/wiki/Tomb_of_Galerius" title="Tomb of Galerius" class="mw-redirect">Tomb of Galerius</a> (the "Rotunda"), at the junction of Iasonidou and Arrianou streets. Its current dedication to Saint Panteleimon was given to the church after the end of <a href="/wiki/Ottoman_Empire" title="Ottoman Empire">Ottoman</a> rule in 1912, and its original dedication is therefore disputed. In Ottoman times, it was converted into a mosque in 1548 and became known as <b>Ishakiye Camii</b> ("Mosque of Ishak [Isaac]"), which in the prevailing scholarly interpretation points to an identification with the late Byzantine <b>Monastery of the Virgin Peribleptos</b>, also known as the <b>Monastery of Kyr Isaac</b> after its <a href="/wiki/Ktetor" title="Ktetor">founder</a> Jacob, who was the city\'s <a href="/wiki/Metropolitan_bishop" title="Metropolitan bishop">metropolitan bishop</a> in 1295–1315 and became a monk with the <a href="/wiki/Monastic_name" title="Monastic name" class="mw-redirect">monastic name</a> of Isaac. A counter-argument however supports the theory that the present church is unrelated to the Peribleptos Monastery, and that it was converted into a mosque ca. 1500, when the city\'s <i><a href="/wiki/Kad%%C4%%B1" title="Kadı">kadı</a></i> (judge), was Ishak Çelebi, whom the mosque was named after. However, the church\'s architecture and decoration, which date to the late 13th/early 14th centuries, appear to support the former view.</p>
            <p>The church is of the tetrastyle <a href="/wiki/Cross-in-square" title="Cross-in-square">cross-in-square</a> type, with a <a href="/wiki/Narthex" title="Narthex">narthex</a> and a (now destroyed) <a href="/wiki/Ambulatory" title="Ambulatory">ambulatory</a> that is connected to two chapels (still extant). Very few of the building\'s original wall paintings survive. Ottoman remains include the base of the demolished minaret and a marble fountain.</p>
        ]]>
        </item>

    </string-array>
</resources>
